<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/co/cities/colorado-springs/mayor/orders/2020-03-10">
  <num type="Proclamation"/>
  <heading>Proclamation and Declaration of Emergency Pursuant to City Charter $ 4-10 and City Code $ 8.7.103 Pertaining to a Public Health Emergency Caused by the 2019 Novel Coronavirus</heading>
  <heading type="oll">Colorado Springs Proclamation and Declaration of Emergency Pursuant to City Charter $ 4-10 and City Code $ 8.7.103 Pertaining to a Public Health Emergency Caused by the 2019 Novel Coronavirus March 16, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-10</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-10.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://coloradosprings.gov/sites/default/files/proclamation_and_declaration_of_emergency_-_mayor_suthers_march_16_2020.pdf"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-16</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>PROCLAMATION AND DECLARATION OF EMERGENCY PURSUANT TO CITY CHARTER $ 4-10 AND CITY CODE $ 8.7.103 PERTAINING TO A PUBLIC HEALTH EMERGENCY CAUSED BY THE 2019 NOVEL CORONAVIRUS Section 1. In accordance with City Charter $ 4-10 and Section 8.7.103 of the Code of the City of Colorado Springs 2001, as amended ("City Code"), a public health emergency caused by confirmed cases in the City of Colorado Springs of the contagious 2019 Novel Coronavirus ("COVID-19") is hereby proclaimed and declared to be in effect since March 10, 2020, and continues to exist as of March 16, 2020, and will continue to exist until terminated pursuant to Section 4 below. Section 2. The Mayor hereby finds, determines, and declares that there is an ongoing risk and likelihood of additional COVID-19 positive patients being identified in the City of Colorado Springs. Based on the foregoing finding, there exists an actual and imminent threat of additional confirmed COVID-19 patients in the City of Colorado Springs and therefore a threat to the public health and safety of the City's residents. This Proclamation and Declaration is necessary for the immediate preservation of the public health, safety, welfare and peace, and to contain the emergency epidemic. City Code $ 8.7.103(A). Section 3. The Director of Emergency Management is authorized to act in accordance with the City's emergency operations plan and to activate any applicable federal, state, or local intergovernmental agreement for mutual or disaster assistance. All departments and divisions of the City, including Colorado Springs Utilities, are directed to cooperate with the Director of Emergency Management and with each other to provide assistance to the citizens of the City of Colorado Springs and to provide emergency and disaster assistance. City Code $ 8.7.103(C). Section 4. This Proclamation and Declaration shall be effective until the Mayor declares that the threat of the public health emergency has passed, or that the public health emergency no longer exists, and that the public health emergency condition is no longer required to receive State and Federal assistance and terminates this Proclamation and Declaration. This Proclamation and Declaration may be reviewed by the City Council ("Council") and may be terminated by the Council at any time by majority vote of the Council. This Proclamation and Declaration shall be effective from March 10, 2020, and continues to exist as of March 16, 2020, at the time indicated below. City Charter $ 3-10(g) and 4-10. Section 5. This Proclamation and Declaration shall be posted in the City Clerk's Office and remain posted until the public health emergency condition no longer necessitates the City to receive State and Federal assistance. This Proclamation and Declaration relating to the COVID19 virus is executed this 16" day of March, 2020 at 10 o'clock am, MDT. Open W Sutters John W. Suthers Mayor, City of Colorado Springs</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
