<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/oh/cities/cleveland/mayor/orders/2020-03-11">
  <num type="Proclamation"/>
  <heading>City of Cleveland Proclamation of Civil Emergency March 11, 2020</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-11</effective>
    <expiration>2020-03-31</expiration>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-11.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://www.dropbox.com/s/hzrsum0h5y50jc8/Proclamation%20of%20Civil%20of%20Emergency%20No.%201_3.11.2020_effective%20215%20pm.pdf?dl=0"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-11</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>CITY OF CLEVELAND Mayor Frank G. Jackson PROCLAMATION OF CIVIL EMERGENCY No. 1 3/11/2020 RECITALS 1. Commencing at 1:00 p.m., 3/11/2020 and continuing to 11:59 p.m., 3/31/2020 the citizens of the City of Cleveland is experiencing a civil emergency due to the need to mitigate the severity and duration of COVID-19 in our City. 2. The problems experienced as a result of this situation endanger the health, safety, and welfare of persons and property within the City of Cleveland and potentially hinder the execution of the ordinances of the City, the laws of the State of Ohio and of the United States. PROCLAMATION NOW, THEREFORE, I, Frank G. Jackson, Mayor of the City of Cleveland, under and by the virtue of the authority vested in me by the Charter and laws of the City of Cleveland, do hereby proclaim that a State of Civil Emergency exists within the City of Cleveland. A. AREA AFFECTED BY THIS PROCLAMATION I hereby proclaim that the entire area within the municipal boundaries of the City of Cleveland is covered by this proclamation. B. LAW ENFORCEMENT ASSISTANCE All regular and auxiliary law enforcement agencies and organizations within and without the City of Cleveland are encouraged to assist in preserving the peace within the City of Cleveland by coordinating activities with Federal, State, and local health officials. C. CIVIL EMERGENCY EXECUTIVE POLICY GROUP There is hereby established a "Civil Emergency Executive Policy Group" consisting of Interim Chief of Staff and Finance Director Sharon Dumas, Chief of Operations Darnell Brown, Chief of Communications, Government and International Affairs Valarie J. Mccall, Chief of Public Affairs Natoya Walker-Minor, Director of Law Barbara A. Langhenry, Director of Health Merle Gordon, Director of Public Safety Michael C. McGrath, and Emergency Operations Center Manager Fred Szabo to perform the following duties: 1. To oversee conditions during the existence of the Civil Emergency; 2. To make recommendations as to additional actions necessary to minimize the adverse impact of the Civil Emergency, including the issuance or amendment of City rules, regulations, and procedures to alleviate or manage in an orderly manner the Civil Emergency; and 3. To make recommendations for the amendment or suspension of any rule of any office, department, division, bureau, board or commission of the City of Cleveland to minimize the adverse impact of the Civil Emergency. The Civil Emergency Executive Policy Group shall make its recommendations to the Mayor and, if the Mayor determines that such actions are necessary, additional orders shall be promulgated for the purpose of implementing the recommendations, provided, however, that any existing rule, regulation, or procedure of the City which is suspended, changed or amended during the existence of the Civil Emergency shall be reinstated as it existed prior to its change by the Mayor upon the expiration of the Civil Emergency and any new rule, regulation, or procedure which is promulgated during the existence of the Civil Emergency shall be of no further effect after the expiration of the Civil Emergency. D. DURATION OF CIVIL EMERGENCY The State of Civil Emergency proclaimed pursuant to this proclamation shall terminate at 11:59 p.m. on 3/31/2020 or upon the issuance of a proclamation by the Mayor that a Civil Emergency no longer exists, whichever occurs first. However, the Mayor may extend the Civil Emergency for such additional periods of time as determined necessary. I, Frank G. Jackson, Mayor of the City of Cleveland, State of Ohio, affix my signature to this Proclamation this _day of March 2020, at 2. o'clock a.m./p.m.. Frank G. Jackson Mayor</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
