<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/tx/cities/el-paso/ordinances/2020-03-17/1">
  <num type="Ordinance"/>
  <heading>Emergency Ordinance Instituting Emergency Measures Due to a Public Health Emergency; Penalty as Provided in Section 8</heading>
  <heading type="oll">City of El Paso, TX Emergency Ordinance Instituting Emergency Measures Due to a Public Health Emergency; Penalty as Provided in Section 8, March 17, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./1.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-17</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>EMERGENCY ORDINANCE INSTITUTING EMERGENCY MEASURES DUE TO A PUBLIC HEALTH EMERGENCY; PENALTY AS PROVIDED IN SECTION 8 BE IT ORDAINED BY THE CITY COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF EL PASO: THAT an emergency exists; and WHEREAS, on March 13, 2020, the Governor of the State of Texas declared a state of disaster and the President of the United States of America declared a national emergency in relation to COVID-19; and WHEREAS, by proclamation issued on March 13, 2020, the Mayor declared a local state of disaster for the City of El Paso resulting from a public health emergency; and WHEREAS, City Charter Section 3.10 allows for the City Council to adopt an emergency ordinance to meet a public emergency affecting, life, health, property or the public peace; and WHEREAS, said state of disaster requires that certain emergency measures be taken pursuant to the Executive Order of the Governor Relating to Emergency Management; therefore, the following regulations shall take effect immediately upon issuance, and shall remain in effect until the state of disaster is terminated: AND BE IT FURTHER ORDAINED BY THE CITY COUNCIL OF EL PASO, TEXAS: That the following is hereby in effect: 1. STATE AND FEDERAL GUIDANCE The City authorizes the Emergency Management Director or designee to update, restrict and promulgate regulations necessary to comply with Federal, State, and Local authorities' guidance in relation to COVID-19. 2. CITY BOARDS AND COMMISSIONS a) Unless required by State law, all City boards and commission meetings are suspended while this ordinance is in effect. b) Any boards and commissions that must meet pursuant to State law should meet pursuant to the Texas Open Meetings Act as provided by the suspension of the Open Meetings Act provisions approved by the Texas Governor and institute best practices in an effort to reduce in person meetings. 3. PRICE CONTROLS A person shall not sell any of the following goods or services for more than the price the person charged for the goods or services on March 13, 2020: a) groceries, beverages, toiletry articles, ice; 20-1052-1069/978306_11/AS/ORDINANCE INSTITUTING EMERGENCY MEASURES b) construction and building materials and supplies, and earthmoving equipment and machinery; c) electrical and gas generating and transmission equipment, parts and accessories; d) charcoal briquettes, matches, candles, lamp illumination and heat unit carbides, dry batteries, light bulbs, flashlights, and hand lanterns; e) hand tools (manual and power), hardware and household supplies, and equipment rental; automotive parts, supplies, and accessories; g) h ) plumbing and electrical tools and supplies; apartment, duplex, multi-family dwelling, rooming house, hotel and motel rental; gasoline, diesel oil, motor oil, kerosene, grease, and automotive lubricants; j) k) restaurant, cafeteria, and boarding-house meals; services of roofing and building contractors, plumbers, electricians, mechanics, tree surgeons, and automobile wrecker companies; 1) medicine, pharmaceutical, and medical equipment and supplies; m) blankets, quilts, bedspreads, bed linens, mattresses, bedsprings, bedsteads, towels, toilet paper; and n) furniture and clothing. 4. SUSPENSION AND MODIDFICATION OF ORDINANCES a) The following ordinances are hereby suspended or modified as indicated: i . Any ordinance or regulation that imposes an obligation upon the City to deliver in less than five (5) business days any non-essential good, or service, as determined by the Mayor, is hereby suspended. ii. Ordinance number 016736 is hereby modified to read as follows: Ordinance granting the authority to the City Manager or designee to enter into and sign certain contracts on behalf of the City is hereby amended to authorize the City Manager to negotiate and enter into contracts, including the issuance of purchase orders, on behalf of the City and sign and bind the City for contracts for the acquisition of goods and services in an amount that exceeds $50,000 per annum, in order to take immediate action to relieve the emergency necessity of the municipality's residents, to preserve the property of the municipality, and to protect the health, safety, and welfare of the municipality's residents. b) The suspension or modifications of the ordinances and regulations listed in Subsection (a) shall remain in effect for 30 days, unless re-enacted in accordance with City Charter 3.10 or until the state of disaster is terminated, whichever is sooner. 5. MOVEMENT OF PEOPLE AND OCCUPANCY OF PREMISES a) Individuals shall limit the size of public or private gatherings to no more than fifty (50) people in a single space. 2 20-1052-1069/978306_11/AS/ORDINANCE INSTITUTING EMERGENCY MEASURES For purposes of clarity, a gathering does not include the following spaces: i. Spaces where persons may be in transit or waiting for transit such as airports and bus terminals; ii. ifi. Office space or residential buildings; Grocery stores, hotels, or other retail establishments where large numbers of people are present, but it is unusual for them to be within arm's length of one another for extended periods; and iv. Hospitals and medical facilities. b) Bars, lounges, taverns, arcades and private clubs shall close. c) Restaurants may remain open pursuant to the following: i. Restaurants shall limit the amount of people on their premises at one time to half of their designated seating maximum occupancy and ensure that tables are at least 6 feet apart from each other. ii. Restaurants shall disinfect and sanitize commonly touched surfaces and non-food contact surfaces at least once every hour. iii. Restaurants shall not allow parties of more than 6 people at one table. iv. Restaurants must adopt and implement a screening policy for food handlers and all employees, and establish protocols for employees exclusion if they develop the following symptoms: 1. Fever greater than 100"F 2. Cough and shortness of breath v. Make available and visible COVID-19 prevent print materials within the restaurant. 6. TEMPORARY ASSISTANCE The City urges all businesses to provide two weeks of paid sick leave to employees that succumb to COVID-19, are caring for someone with COVID-19, or are subject to quarantine. The City further urges businesses to apply for any available federal funding for the provision of paid sick leave. 7. UTILITIES &amp; RESIDENCE a) No local utility shall discontinue the provision of cable, internet, water, gas, waste removal and electric utility services to a local resident for lack of payment while this ordinance is in effect. b) To the extent allowed by law, no landlord shall evict a tenant for lack of payment while this ordinance is in effect. 8. PENALTIES a) These regulations shall have the effect of ordinances when duly filed with the City Clerk. 3 20-1052-1069/978306_11/AS/ORDINANCE INSTITUTING EMERGENCY MEASURES b) A person who violates any provision of these regulations, upon conviction, is guilty of a misdemeanor punishable by a fine of not more than five hundred dollars ($500.00). 9. EMERGENCY This emergency ordinance shall take effect immediately upon its adoption and publication and it is accordingly so ordained. This ordinance shall remain in effect for 30 days, unless re-enacted in accordance with City Charter section 3.10 or until the state of disaster is terminated, whichever is sooner. 10. SEVERABILITY CLAUSE It is hereby declared to be the intention of the City Council that the phrases, sentences, paragraphs and sections of this ordinance are severable. If any part of this ordinance shall be declared unconstitutional by the valid judgment or decree of any court of competent jurisdiction, such unconstitutionality shall not affect the remaining phrases, sentences, paragraphs and sections. PASSED AND ADOPTED, this 17th day of March, 2020. THE CITY OF EL PASO, TEXAS Dee Margo a Mayor of the City of El Paso ATTESTS Laura D.Pune Laura D. Prine City Clerk APPROVED AS TO FORM: Karla M. Nistan City Attorney 20-1052-1069/978306_11/AS/ORDINANCE INSTITUTING EMERGENCY MEASURES</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
