<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/tx/cities/el-paso/ordinances/2020-03-17/2">
  <num type="Ordinance"/>
  <heading>An Emergency Ordinance of the City of El Paso, Texas Extending a Disaster Declaration Due to a Public Health Emegency</heading>
  <heading type="oll">An Emergency Ordinance of the City of El Paso, Texas Extending a Disaster Declaration Due to a Public Health Emegency, March 17, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration>2020-04-16</expiration>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-17</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>AN EMERGENCY ORDINANCE OF THE CITY OF EL PASO, TEXAS EXTENDING A DISASTER DECLARATION DUE TO A PUBLIC HEALTH EMEGENCY BE IT ORDAINED BY THE CITY COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF EL PASO: WHEREAS, on March 13, 2020, the Governor of the State of Texas declared a state of disaster and the President of the United States of America declared a national emergency in relation to COVID-19; and WHEREAS, on March 13, 2020 the Mayor signed a Local Emergency Declaration and requested the aid of the State Government pursuant to Texas Government Code Section 418.108; and WHEREAS, as of March 16, 2020 there were three COVID-19 presumptive positive tests confirmed in El Paso; and WHEREAS, the World Health Organization Director General urged aggressive preparedness and activation of emergency plans to aggressively change the trajectory of this epidemic; and WHEREAS, $418.108(b) of the Texas Government Code provides that a local state of disaster may not be continued for a period in excess of seven days without the consent of the governing body of the political subdivision; and WHEREAS, City Charter Section 3.10 allows for the City Council to adopt an emergency ordinance to meet a public emergency affecting, life, health, property or the public peace; and WHEREAS, the condition necessitating declaration of a state of disaster continues to exist. NOW THEREFORE, BE IT ORDAINED BY THE CITY COUNCIL OF EL PASO, TEXAS: 1. That the state of disaster proclaimed for the City of El Paso by the Mayor on March 13, 2020 shall continue for thirty (30) days unless re-enacted in accordance with City Charter Section 3.10 or until terminated by order of the City Council, whichever is sooner. 2. This ordinance is adopted as an emergency measure with the unanimous vote of the City Council Representatives present and the consent of the Mayor and pursuant to City Charter section 3.10 and shall become effective on the 17th day of March, 2020. PASSED AND ADOPTED, this 17th day of March, 2020. [Signatures on the following page] THE CITY OF EL PASO, TEXAS 20-1052-1069/977941_2/AS/Emergency Ordinance DEE MARGO Mayor of the City of El Paso ATTEST: Laura D tripe Laura D. Prine City Clerk APPROVED AS TO FORM: Karla M. Nieman City Attorney 20-1052-1069/977941_2/AS/Emergency Ordinance</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
