<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="Mayoral Order" id="us/fl/cities/tampa/mayor/orders/2020-03-17">
  <num type="Mayoral Order">1</num>
  <heading>COVID-19 - Limitation on Hours and on Premise Consumption of Food and Beverages in Restaurants, Bars, Clubs and Other Establishments</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-17.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://www.tampagov.net/sites/default/files/public%3A/additionalfiles/mayoralorder-1-covid-19.pdf"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-17</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>CITY CITY OF TAMPA OFFICE OF THE MAYOR Jane Castor, Mayor March 17, 2020 MAYORAL ORDER # 1 ISSUED PURSUANT TO CITY OF TAMPA EXECUTIVE ORDER 2020-02 COVID-19: Limitation on Hours and On-Premises Consumption of Food and Beverages in Restaurants, Bars, Private Clubs and Other Establishments; and Limitation on Size of Gatherings WHEREAS, Declarations of Emergency to institute measures to prevent the spread of COVID-19 have been issued by the President of the United States, the Governor of the State of Florida, the Mayor of the City of Tampa and the Hillsborough County Emergency Policy Group; and WHEREAS, public health experts have consistently recommended avoiding close physical interaction between people in order to slow the spread of COVID-19, and the U.S. Centers for Disease Control ("CDC") has continuously updated its social distancing guidelines; and WHEREAS, this Mayoral Order is consistent with the Executive Order of the Hillsborough County Emergency Policy Group, and Hillsborough County Administrator Orders, and Executive Orders issued by the Governor of the State of Florida to address the spread of COVID-19, particularly the imminent threat posed by close social interaction; and NOW THEREFORE, pursuant to the authority vested in me by Chapter 252, Fla.Stat., Article VII (Civil Emergencies), Section 2-401, et. seq. of the City of Tampa Code of Ordinances, and City of Tampa Executive Order 2020-02, Section 1: I hereby issue the following order, effective within the limits of the City of Tampa, as of the date set forth below: A. All restaurants, private clubs, bars (subject to the restrictions in B. below), or other establishments that offer food or drink for sale for on-premises consumption shall close for business daily at or before 10:00 PM and remain closed until at least 6:00 AM the following day 306 East Jackson Street . Tampa, Florida 33602 . (813) 274-8251 . Fax: (813) 274-7050 or such other time as opening may be permitted pursuant to law or permit. [Hillsborough County Administrator Order] B. Any establishment authorized by state license to sell alcoholic beverages for consumption on premises, that derives more than 50% of its gross revenue from the sale of alcoholic beverages, shall suspend all sale of alcoholic beverages for thirty days, effective at 5:00 PM March 17, 2020. Governor's Executive Order 20-68] C. In addition to the above, any restaurant, including private clubs or other establishments that offer food for sale for on-premises consumption shall limit their occupancy to 50% of their current building occupancy during all permitted hours of operation. Such establishments may continue to offer food and non-alcoholic beverages for take-out and by delivery, subject to adherence to all sanitation and social distancing protocols for COVID-19 as set forth in Centers for Disease Control and Florida Department of Health guidance. [Hillsborough County Administrator Order] D. Restaurants shall follow the CDC guidance by ensuring, at a minimum, a 6-foot distance between any group of patrons, and by limiting parties to no more than 10 individuals. [Governor's Executive Order 20-68] E. All public or private gatherings, including community, civic, public leisure, faith-based events, sporting events, concerts and similar events that bring together more than 50 people in a single room or single space at the same time are prohibited. [Hillsborough County Administrator Order] F. The limitation set forth in E. above, shall apply to venues such as fitness centers, health clubs, private recreational clubs and theaters, but does not include venues that provide essential goods or services such as grocery stores, hospitals or other facilities that provide medical care, pharmacies, gas stations, bank/credit unions, and shelters, or to those establishments to which the restrictions set forth in C. above apply. [Hillsborough County Administrator Order] G. All Public beaches (excluding boat ramps) shall be closed to the Public. [Governor's Executive Order 20-68] Section 2. The City of Tampa, in coordination with County, State and Federal agencies, will continue to monitor this fluid situation and may impose further restrictions as necessary, including the closure of various establishments, the operation of which may create the risk of the spread of COVID-19. Section 3. This Order constitutes a directive per Executive Order 2020-02, and Sec. 2-401, et.seq. City of Tampa Code of Ordinances. Pursuant to Fla.Stat. $ 252.50, a violation of this order is a second degree misdemeanor which carries a penalty of up to 60 days imprisonment and/or a $500 fine. DONE and ORDERED this ! 1 day of March 2020. Are Castor Jane Castor, Mayor 2</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
