<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/fl/cities/miami/mayor/orders/2020-03-12">
  <num type="Declaration"/>
  <heading>City of Miami Declaration of State of Local Emergency March 12, 2020</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-12</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-12.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://www.miamigov.com/files/sharedassets/public/news/2020/2020-03-12-covid-19-emergency-declaration.pdf"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-12</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>HE CITY OF MIAN LORID CITY OF MIAMI DECLARATION OF STATE OF LOCAL EMERGENCY WHEREAS, Florida Governor Ron Desantis in accordance with Article IV Section (1)(a) of the Florida Constitution and Chapter 252, Florida Statutes, promulgated Emergency Order 20-52 to declare a state of emergency in the State of Florida in response to Novel Coronavirus ("COVID-19"); and WHEREAS, COVID-19 may require extraordinary and immediate actions by the City of Miami in order to protect the public health, safety, and welfare; and WHEREAS, pursuant to Section 4(g)(3) of the Charter of the City of Miami, Florida ("City Charter") the Mayor may declare a State of Emergency in time of public emergency as provided in state law and Chapter 252.38.(3)(a) Florida Statutes, authorizes political subdivisions to declare and enact a State of Local Emergency thereby waiving the procedures and formalities otherwise required of the political subdivision by law, and; THEREFORE, as Mayor of the City of Miami and pursuant to the authority vested in the Office of the Mayor by virtue of $4(g)(3), of the City Charter, I hereby declare a State of Local Emergency. This State of Local Emergency includes all of the City of Miami. Pursuant to this Declaration, the City Manager is hereby ordered to take whatever prudent actions are necessary to protect the health, safety, and welfare of the community. Enacted: Signed: Francis X. Suarez, Mayor of the City of Miami Date: 3/12 / 2020 Time : 2:15 mmm . Attest: Todd Hannort, City Clerk Form la CERTIFICATE OF SERVICE , JEREMIAH WILLIAM JOHNEM, HEREBY CERTIFY that the attached and foregoing DECLARATION OF A STATE OF LOCAL EMERGENCY was filed with the City Clerk of the City of Miami, Florida on the 12th day of March, 2020. Signature of person filing with City Clerk) Form 1b E CITY OF MIA TWVI INCORPORATED LORID NOTICE OF LOCAL EMERGENCY MEASURES Under the provisions of law and $252.31 - 252.60, Florida Statutes, the Mayor of the City of Miami, declared on March 12, 2020 at 2 - /5 0m ' that a State of Local Emergency exists within the City of Miami, Miami-Dade County, Florida. There is reason to believe that there exists a clear and present danger of substantial injury to health, safety, and welfare of persons or to property, all of which constitute an imminent threat to public peace and order and to the general welfare of this City, thereby the attached Local Emergency Measures are necessary and hereby instituted. All persons within the said City are advised to become informed as to the contents of the attached Local Emergency Measures and to keep informed as to the issuance of further Local Supplementary Emergency Orders. Violations of the Local Emergency Order or the Local Supplementary Emergency Orders will subject persons to arrest and conviction thereof to the penalties as provided by law. 3/ 12 / 2020 2:15 pm Print Name: Stophace Severino Date &amp; Time of original declaration of State of Emergency. Form 2c THE CITY OF MIA LORID NOTICE OF PROCLAMATION AND DECLARATION OF A STATE OF LOCAL EMERGENCY Under the provisions of law and $252.31 - 252.60, Florida Statutes, the Mayor of the City of Miami, has on March 12, 2020 at 2: /5 pamdeclared that a State of Local Emergency exists within the City of Miami, Miami-Dade County, Florida. All persons within the said City are advised to become informed as to the contents of the above Declaration of a State of Local Emergency and to keep informed as to the provisions of the Local Supplementary Emergency Orders, if the same be issued. Violations of the Local Emergency Orders or the Local Supplementary Emergency Orders will subject persons to arrest and upon conviction thereof to the penalties as provided by law. fix (Signature of person providing news media with copy) Form Ic THE CITY OF MIA LORID DECLARATION OF LOCAL EMERGENCY MEASURES IMPLEMENTED BY THE CITY MANAGER OF THE CITY OF MIAMI, OF MIAMI-DADE COUNTY, FLORIDA I, Arthur Noriega V, City Manager of the City of Miami, County of Miami-Dade, State of Florida, acting under the authority granted to municipalities by Florida Statutes, Sections 252.38, et seq., 501.160 and the authority granted to me by Chapter 4(g)(3) of the City of Miami Charter and by Chapter 45 of the Miami City Code, and Chapter 8A-5 of the Miami Dade County Code, and having determined that because of COVID-19 is a natural emergency whose effects are or will be felt within the City and that on account thereof there is reason to believe that it is necessary to take whatever prudent action is necessary to ensure the health, safety, and welfare of the City do hereby proclaim and declare that a state of local emergency exists within the City of Miami, County of Miami- Dade, State of Florida, and the attached and selected emergency measures are necessary and are hereby instituted. Arthur Noriega V, City Manager City of Miami, Florida Date: March 12, 2020 Time: 2:15 Am . Form 2a Local Emergency Measures The below Emergency Measures are hereby instituted due to the declaration and proclamation that a State of Local Emergency exists within the City of Miami, County of Miami-Dade, Florida. CLOSING OF PLACES OF ASSEMBLAGE IN THE CITY 1 . As City Manager I hereby authorize the closure of places of public assemblage, with designated exceptions. 2. Assemblage by any person or persons in such closed place is hereby prohibited. BAN ON UNCONSCIONABLE PRICING (PRICE GOUGING) 1 . No person shall during a declared state of local emergency impose unconscionable prices for any essential commodity, including but not limited to goods, supplies, services, provisions, materials, resources, equipment, or any article of commerce and includes, without limitation water, food, ice, chemicals, petroleum products, and lumber necessary for consumption and/or use as a direct result of the emergency. 2 . No person shall during a declared state of local emergency impose unconscionable prices for the rental or lease of any dwelling unit or storage facility. Arthur Noriega V, City Manager City of Miami, Florida Date: March 12, 2020 Time: 2:15 p.m . Form 2b (Initialed by Emergency Manager or Designce) Page 1 of 1</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
