<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/ca/cities/fresno/mayor/orders/2020-03-16">
  <num type="Proclamation"/>
  <heading>A Proclamation of the Mayor of Fresno, California Declaring a Local Emergency</heading>
  <heading type="oll">A Proclamation of the Mayor of Fresno, California Declaring a Local Emergency March 16, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-16</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-16.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-16</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>A PROCLAMATION OF THE MAYOR OF THE CITY OF FRESNO, CALIFORNIA, DECLARING A LOCAL EMERGENCY WHEREAS, Fresno Municipal Code Section 2-503 empowers the Mayor to proclaim the existence or threatened existence of a local emergency when the City is affected or likely to be affected by a public calamity and the Council is not in session; and WHEREAS, the Mayor does hereby find that conditions of extreme peril to the safety of persons and property have arisen with respect to the international COVID-19 pandemic, with emergency orders provided by the U.S. Government and State of California; and WHEREAS, the City must take all necessary and appropriate action to limit exposure to further infection; and WHEREAS, the City shall apply to all appropriate agencies for relief funding for necessary services, and relief for public and private employees for lost income. NOW, THEREFORE, IT IS HEREBY PROCLAIMED that a local emergency now exists throughout the City; and IT IS FURTHER PROCLAIMED AND ORDERED that during the existence of the local emergency the powers, functions, and duties of the emergency organization of this City shall be those prescribed by state law, by ordinances, and resolutions of this City; and IT IS FURTHER PROCLAIMED AND ORDERED that a copy of this Proclamation be forwarded to the Emergency Services Director of the County of Fresno, the State Director of the Office of Emergency Services, and the Governor of California. Dated: 316- 2020 By: Lee Brand, Mayor 1 of 1</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
