<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Louisville Executive Order" id="us/ky/cities/louisville/mayor/orders/2020-001">
  <num type="Executive Order">2020-001</num>
  <heading>Declaration of a State of Emergency Relating to Preparations and Responsive Measures Regarding the Novel Coronavirus (COVID-19)</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-13</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-001.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-13</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>OFFICE OF THE MAYOR LOUISVILLE, KENTUCKY EXECUTIVE ORDER NO. 2020-001 March 13, 2020 DECLARATION OF A STATE OF EMERGENCY RELATING TO PREPARATIONS AND RESPONSIVE MEASURES REGARDING THE NOVEL CORONAVIRUS (COVID-19) WHEREAS, the World Health Organization has declared a global pandemic related to novel coronavirus (COVID-19) which has killed thousands and is expected to increase exponentially across the world; and WHEREAS, a case of COVID-19 have been confirmed in Louisville Metro as of the date of this ORDER, and multiple cases have been confirmed in the Commonwealth of Kentucky, with that number expected to increase exponentially; and WHEREAS, the coronavirus (COVID-19) continues to pose a threat to the public health and safety of the citizens of Louisville Metro. The impact of the coronavirus (COVID-19) and attendant consequences are being felt across Louisville Metro, and additional measures are needed to address these challenges; and WHEREAS, as Mayor, I intend to invoke any and all powers at my disposal to combat, contain, and slow the spread of this condition in order to protect the residents of Louisville Metro; and WHEREAS, the Governor of the Commonwealth of Kentucky has issued several Executive Orders and may issue more in order to implement measures to address the response to the coronavirus (COVID-19) crisis, including but not limited to Executive Order 2020-15, issued on March 6, 2020, which has declared that a state of emergency exists in the Commonwealth of Kentucky; and WHEREAS, the Attorney General has urged residents to report any instances of price gouging to his office for investigation; and WHEREAS, the law of the Commonwealth of Kentucky vests the Chief Executive Officer of a consolidated local government with the authority to declare an emergency, so as to legally invoke and implement the exercise of extraordinary emergency powers in the manner necessary to protect our residents; and WHEREAS, this medical pandemic makes it prudent and necessary to declare an emergency and implement measures that are designed to combat, contain, and slow the spread of the coronavirus (COVID-19) in the manner set out in this Executive Order. NOW, THEREFORE, I, Greg Fischer, as Mayor of Louisville/Jefferson County Metro Government and, pursuant to Chapters 39A and 39B of the Kentucky Revised Statutes, HEREBY DECLARE that an EMERGENCY exists within Louisville Metro related to the public health of our citizens due to the coronavirus (COVID-19). To that end, I hereby ORDER AND DIRECT THE FOLLOWING: 1. That, effective today, Louisville Metro hereby adopts the Emergency Sick Leave policy (Section 16.16) (attached hereto as Exhibit A). The purpose of this policy is to allow employees who are symptomatic of the coronavirus to remain home and not report to work, and continue to be paid even if they do not possess any sick days to cover their absences. This action will eliminate the need for a sick or potentially sick employee to report to work which could potentially endanger his or her fellow co-workers and the residents of Louisville Metro. I hereby direct the Director of Louisville Metro's Human Resources agency to fully implement, interpret and, if necessary, modify this policy, to accomplish the purposes set forth in this paragraph. 2. That the Chiefs of the agencies of Louisville Metro who are responsible for executing the operations of government and the provision of essential services to our residents are hereby directed to comply with the guidelines issued by the Center for Disease Control and the recommendations of the Department of Public Health and Wellness. These guidelines and recommendations include, but are not limited to, social distancing, tele-commuting (where appropriate), and staggered staff work hours to minimize human contact. The Chiefs of the agencies of Louisville Metro are also directed to shift responsibilities and amend duties of our Metro employees, as necessary and appropriate, so as to ensure that city duties and services are continuously delivered to our residents. All actions taken should be in conjunction with and approved by the Louisville Metro Human Resources Department. 3. That the Department of Procurement of Louisville Metro is hereby empowered, pursuant to KRS Chapters 39A and 39B, to procure any goods and services and take other necessary actions to ensure public health and safety for Louisville Metro employees and our citizens. I further direct the Office of Management and Budget to engage and work with the Metro Council to re- direct funding from the current budget to assist Metro agencies in addressing issues related to the coronavirus (COVID-19) outbreak. 4. That all agencies of Louisville Metro that issue permits related to public gatherings review all permits that have been issued for events for the next 30 days. If, after review, and in accordance with the guidelines issued by the Center for Disease Control 2 and the Department of Public Health and Wellness, it is determined that said permits should be revoked for the health and well-being of our residents, then they shall be revoked immediately. 5. That this Executive Order shall be interpreted, if necessary, to be consistent and in harmony with any and all ORDERS issued by the Governor of the Commonwealth of Kentucky. This ORDER shall remain in effect for 30 days from the date of execution. GREG FISCHER MAYOR APPROVED FOR FORM &amp; LEGALITY MICHAEL J. O'CONNELL JEFFERSON COUNTY ATTORNEY Sarah J. Martin DATE: 3- 13- 20 W EXHIBIT " A" Louisville Metro Government Effective 03/xx/2020 Personnel Policies 16.16 Emergency Sick Leave 16.16(1) In the event that the Mayor declares a state of emergency to be in effect owing to a medical pandemic, symptomatic employees or employees under medically directed isolation shall receive up to ten (10) calendar days of paid emergency sick leave. A. Employees are symptomatic if they display symptoms as described by health professionals from the federal, state, or local government, and can vary by the nature of the specific epidemic. B. FMLA leave is not required to use the full ten (10) days of emergency sick leave. 16.16(2) Employees shall notify their supervisor or the individual(s) designated by the agency to request sick leave per Personnel Policy 16.2 Sick Leave. 16.16(3) Once an employee has used all of emergency sick leave, then they may use their accrued sick leave per Personnel Policy 16.2 Sick Leave. 16.16(4) If an employee's position allows teleworking, the employee may telework using intermittent regular time while symptomatic: however, under no circumstances shall Emergency Sick Leave exceed ten (10) calendar days.</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
