<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Denver Proclamation" id="us/co/cities/denver/council/resolutions/2020-03-23">
  <num type="Proclamation">20-0299</num>
  <heading>A Proclamation Recognizing Workers Providing Critical Services During the COVID-19 Emergency.</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-03-23</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-23.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://denver.legistar.com/LegislationDetail.aspx?From=Alert&amp;ID=4398498&amp;GUID=3F736E28-1654-45F2-B827-9AEEE9ABFF79&amp;Options=ID|Text|&amp;Search=COVID-19"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-23</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>PROCLAMATION City and County of Denver Proclamation No. 20-0299 Recognizing Workers Providing Critical Services During the COVID-19 Emergency WHEREAS, Colorado's grocery workers, food processing employees, healthcare professionals, airport employees, bus drivers, and law enforcement are on the front lines of our response to the COVID-19 pandemic and are meeting critical community needs and ensuring continuity of services; and WHEREAS, workers in these industries are uniquely exposed to COVID-19 because of their essential work and in serving the public cannot self-distance as recommended by the CDC; and WHEREAS, many of these workers are not provided health insurance during their first year of employment, are not offered paid leave in the event they become sick, and have raised alarm about a lack of personal protective equipment at their workspaces; and WHEREAS, failure to address these deficiencies will harm workers and their families and present a substantial risk to the public at large; and WHEREAS, workplaces must take steps to protect the physical health and economic well being of these employees who are most vulnerable to the coronavirus and also doing the most to provide our community with vital goods and services. NOW THEREFORE, BE IT PROCLAIMED BY THE COUNCIL OF THE CITY AND COUNTY OF DENVER: Section 1. That the Council of the City and County of Denver recognizes the incredible sacrifice and hard work being carried out in times of fear and uncertainty and urges workplaces to do the utmost to protect employees who continue to serve our community during these difficult times. Section 2. That the Clerk of the City and County of Denver shall affix the seal of the City and County of Denver to this proclamation and that a copy be transmitted to Governor Polis. PASSED BY THE COUNCIL March 23, 2020 PRESIDENT</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
