<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Minneapolis Resolution" id="us/mn/cities/minneapolis/council/resolutions/2020-03-19">
  <num type="Resolution">2020-001</num>
  <heading>Approving and Extending the Mayor's Declaration of Local Public Health Emergency Resulting from Imminent Health Conditions Caused by the Presence of the Coronavirus Disease (covid-19).</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-03-21</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-19.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://lims.minneapolismn.gov/File/2020-00391"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-19</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>RESOLUTION #1 By Bender, Reich, Gordon, Fletcher, Cunningham, Ellison, Warsame, Goodman, Jenkins, Cano, Schroeder, Johnson, and Palmisano Approving and extending the Mayor's Declaration of Local Public Health Emergency resulting from imminent health conditions caused by the presence of the Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19). Whereas, the City of Minneapolis, Minnesota, has a current local public health emergency resulting from imminent health conditions caused by presence of the Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19); and Whereas, the City of Minneapolis is a public entity within the State of Minnesota; and Whereas, the Center for Disease Control identifies the potential public health threat posed by COVID-19, and has advised that person-to-person spread of COVID-19 will continue to occur; and Whereas, the State of Minnesota has confirmed multiple positive test results for COVID-19, including the Minneapolis-St. Paul greater metropolitan area and Hennepin County; and Whereas, the United States and the State of Minnesota have both declared states of emergencies related to urgent conditions created by the presence of COVID-19; and Whereas, the necessary resources to respond to and recover from the COVID-19 pandemic may exceed the resources available in the City of Minneapolis; and Whereas, the City of Minneapolis is at a very high risk for significant community spread of COVID-19, based on data from the Minnesota Department of Health, as confirmed by the Minneapolis Department of Health and federal health authorities, which has resulted in specific recommendations from the City's Health Department regarding sizes and formats of public gatherings; and Whereas, the presence of COVID-19 may have the potential to compromise the provision of essential City services, including a reduction in the size of the workforce due to school closures, isolation, or quarantine; and Whereas, pursuant to the provisions set forth in Minnesota Statutes, Chapter 12.29, and the Minneapolis Code of Ordinances, Section 128.50, Mayor Frey declared a state of local public health emergency within the City of Minneapolis on Monday, March 16, 2020, to be and remain in force and effect beginning that date and continuing for as long as the State of Minnesota peacetime emergency declaration remains in effect, pending the initial ratification of the City Council within seventy-two (72) hours of the declaration, as required by law; and Whereas, during the declared state of local public health emergency, Mayor Frey proclaimed Emergency Regulation No. 2020-1, adopting and incorporating by reference the terms and conditions of the Governor's Executive Order 20-04 as a corresponding emergency regulation for the City of Minneapolis, providing for temporary closure of bars, restaurants, and other places of public accommodations commencing on Tuesday, March 17, 2020; and Whereas, during the declared state of local public health emergency, Mayor Frey proclaimed Emergency Regulation No. 2020-2, authorizing an exception to state and local procurement policies and procedures in order to expedite the purchase of goods and services reasonably related to the declared local public health emergency, including but not limited to provisions relating to low bids, cooperative contracts, obtaining multiple quotes, and requests for proposals when in the opinion of the City it is in the best interests of the City and for good value to (1) enter into contracts, (2) incur obligations, (3) obtain professional services, (4) rent equipment, and (5) purchase supplies and materials; and Whereas, during the declared state of local public health emergency, Mayor Frey proclaimed Emergency Regulation No. 2020-3, amending Emergency Regulation No. 2020-1 by including within the list of ambit places of public accommodation subject to the original regulation the following additional type of use: any center, facility, or business commonly referred to as an "adult day care," including but not limited to any use categorized in local zoning regulation as a "development achievement center" or licensed by the Minnesota Department of Human Services as "family adult day services"; and Whereas, during the declared state of local public health emergency, Mayor Frey proclaimed Emergency Regulation 2020-4, prohibiting the filing or acceptance of any new land use applications pursuant to Titles 20, 22, and 23 of the Minneapolis Code of Ordinances, in order to ensure compliance with Minnesota Statutes $ 15.99; and pursuant to the City's duly established application requirements, will not deem any application complete hereunder; and Whereas, during the declared state of local public health emergency, Mayor Frey proclaimed Emergency Regulation 2020-5, waiving late fees which may accrue from March 17, 2020, attendant to the renewal of any food, taxi, liquor, wine, beer, or catering license issued by the City of Minneapolis and its Business Licensing Division; Now, Therefore, Be It Resolved by The City Council of The City of Minneapolis: That in accordance with Section 128.50 of the Minneapolis Code of Ordinances (Declaration of Emergency), the City Council does hereby ratify the state of local public health emergency proclaimed by Mayor Frey on Monday, March 16, 2020, pertaining to the City of Minneapolis and all its residents. That the declared state of local public health emergency shall continue and does hereby remain in force and in effect for the same time period as the peacetime emergency declaration issued by Governor Walz for the State of Minnesota, or until such time as the City Council, by official action, may further extend or terminate the declared state of local public health emergency for the City of Minneapolis. That pursuant to Minneapolis Code of Ordinances, Section 128.80, the Mayor's Emergency Regulations Nos. 2020-1, 2020-2, 2020-3, 2020-4, and 2020-5 are hereby ratified and shall be extended throughout the duration of the declared state of local public health emergency, until such time as they may be renewed by further action of the Mayor, or until such time as the City Council, by official action, may further extend or terminate said emergency regulations. Be It Further Resolved that the City Council hereby directs the City Clerk to publish and post this resolution ratifying the declared state of local public health emergency in the City of Minneapolis, including posting on the City's website and official bulletin boards.</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
