<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Minneapolis Emergency Regulation" id="us/mn/cities/minneapolis/mayor/orders/2020-03-17e">
  <num type="Emergency Regulation">2020-005</num>
  <heading/>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status/>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-17e.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://lims.minneapolismn.gov/Download/File/3463/Emergency%20Regulation%202020-5.pdf"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-16</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>SEAL OF NATH STIG Emergency Regulation Issued pursuant to MCO Section 128.60 I, Jacob Frey, Mayor of the City of Minneapolis, subject to the authority granted to me pursuant to Minnesota Statutes, Ch. 12.29, and Minneapolis Code of Ordinances (MCO), Sections 128.50 and 128.60 do hereby proclaim the following Emergency Regulation: PROCLAMATION OF THE MAYOR Emergency Regulation No. 2020-5 Whereas, on March 16, 2020, I declared a local public health emergency related to the COVID-19 pandemic in the City of Minneapolis and assumed executive responsibilities attendant thereto; and Whereas, pursuant to the authority granted to me pursuant to Minnesota Statutes, Ch. 12.29, and Minneapolis Code of Ordinances, Sections 128.50 and 128.60, I am authorized to promulgate emergency regulations to protect the public health, safety, and welfare during this declared emergency; NOW, THEREFORE, I, Jacob Frey, Mayor of the City of Minneapolis, do hereby order the following emergency regulation: In order to ensure operational continuity and continued business capacity during this period of declared emergency and the continued maintenance of certain business licenses when the City may not be able to receive and process related applications within normal time frames, any late fees which may accrue from the effective date of this Emergency Regulation attendant to the renewal of any food, taxi, liquor, wine, beer or catering license issued by the City of Minneapolis and its Business Licensing Division shall be and is hereby waived. MAR 1 7 2020 Date F MINNEA J . SEAL OF TH CITYONE ATTEST: sriod City Clerk 1878 .'NNIW PPROVED JUNE 5TH 181 POSTED: MAR 1 7 2020</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
