<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Minneapolis Emergency Regulation" id="us/mn/cities/minneapolis/mayor/orders/2020-03-17d">
  <num type="Emergency Regulation">2020-004</num>
  <heading/>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status/>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-17d.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://lims.minneapolismn.gov/Download/File/3462/Emergency%20Regulation%202020-4.pdf"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-16</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>THE CITY OF MINNEND NATH 'STIOIN Emergency Regulation Issued pursuant to MCO Section 128.60 I, Jacob Frey, Mayor of the City of Minneapolis, subject to the authority granted to me pursuant to Minnesota Statutes, Ch. 12.29, and Minneapolis Code of Ordinances (MCO), Sections 128.50 and 128.60 do hereby proclaim the following Emergency Regulation: PROCLAMATION OF THE MAYOR Emergency Regulation No. 2020-4 Whereas, on March 16, 2020, I declared a local public health emergency related to the COVID-19 pandemic in the City of Minneapolis and assumed executive responsibilities attendant thereto; and Whereas, pursuant to the authority granted to me pursuant to Minnesota Statutes, Ch. 12.29, and Minneapolis Code of Ordinances, Sections 128.50 and 128.60, I am authorized to promulgate emergency regulations to protect the public health, safety, and welfare during this declared emergency; Whereas, many staff throughout the City enterprise, including those that would conduct the intake, processing, and review of various forms of land use applications, are working remotely and in other forms of flexible work arrangements due to the declared emergency; Whereas, the form and schedule of future meetings of the City's land use-related boards and commissions remains in flux, as well as the ability to ensure a quorum of board or commission members will be present; Whereas, zoning-related land use applications are subject to Minn. Stat. $ 15.99 ("60-Day Law"); NOW, THEREFORE, I, Jacob Frey, Mayor of the City of Minneapolis, do hereby order the following emergency regulation: In order to ensure operational continuity and continued business capacity during this period of declared emergency and to ensure compliance with Minn. Stat. $ 15.99, the City shall not accept or process any new and use applications submitted in any form pursuant to the Minneapolis Code of Ordinances, Titles 20, 22, and/or 23. Pursuant to the City's duly established application requirements, the City will also not deem any application complete hereunder. MAR 1 7 2020 THE CITYARY Addy . SEAL OF THE DOT MINNEAPO Siste City Clerk PROVED JUNE 5TH 187 POLIS, MINN. . 848 ATTEST: HAR 1 7 2020 POSTED:</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
