<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Minneapolis Emergency Regulation" id="us/mn/cities/minneapolis/mayor/orders/2020-03-17c">
  <num type="Emergency Regulation">2020-003</num>
  <heading/>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status/>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-17c.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://lims.minneapolismn.gov/Download/File/3461/Emergency%20Regulation%202020-3.pdf"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-16</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>. SEAL OF THE 10 . NATH'STION Emergency Regulation Issued pursuant to MCO Section 128.60 I, Jacob Frey, Mayor of the City of Minneapolis, subject to the authority granted to me pursuant to Minnesota Statutes, Ch. 12.29, and Minneapolis Code of Ordinances (MCO), Sections 128.50 and 128.60 do hereby proclaim the following Emergency Regulation: PROCLAMATION OF THE MAYOR Emergency Regulation No. 2020-3 Whereas, on March 16, 2020, I declared a local public health emergency related to the COVID-19 pandemic in the City of Minneapolis and assumed executive responsibilities attendant thereto; and Whereas, pursuant to the authority granted to me pursuant to Minnesota Statutes, Ch. 12.29, and Minneapolis Code of Ordinances, Sections 128.50 and 128.60, I am authorized to promulgate emergency regulations to protect the public health, safety, and welfare during this declared emergency; and Whereas, on March 16, the Governor of the State of Minnesota issued Emergency Executive Order 20-04 providing for the temporary closure of bars, restaurants, and other places of public accommodation; and Whereas, City of Minneapolis law enforcement and local public health authorities are charged with monitoring and enforcing Executive Order 20-04 as long as it remains in effect; Whereas, on March 16, I promulgated Emergency Regulation No. 2020-1 that adopted and incorporated by reference Executive Order 20-04. NOW, THEREFORE, I, Jacob Frey, Mayor of the City of Minneapolis, do hereby amend Emergency Regulation No. 2020-1 to include within the ambit of places of public accommodation subject to the order the following additional type of use: any center, facility, or business commonly referred to as an "adult day care center," including but not limited to any use categorized in local zoning regulation as a "development achievement center" or licensed by the Minnesota Department of Human Services as "family adult day services." MAR 1 7 2020 Date Jacob Frey Mayor of Minneapolis CITY OF MINNEHA ATTEST: SEAL OF TH POLIS, Canyon POSTED: PROVED JU 878 . NNIW MAR 1 7 2020</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
