<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Seattle Resolution" id="us/wa/cities/seattle/council/resolutions/2020-03-16">
  <num type="Resolution (Res)">31938</num>
  <heading>A Resolution Modifying the March 14, 2020 Emergency Order Relating to Residential Evictions.</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-03-16</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-16.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="http://seattle.legistar.com/LegislationDetail.aspx?From=Alert&amp;ID=4397115&amp;GUID=D7D180FC-D90A-4560-A5CE-04896DA37FB8&amp;Options=ID|Text|&amp;Search=COVID-19"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-16</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>SEATTLE CITY COUNCIL Legislative Summary Res 31938 Record No.: Res 31938 Type: Resolution (Res) Status: Adopted Version: 2 Ord. no: In Control: City Clerk File Created: 03/16/2020 Final Action: 03/16/2020 Title: A RESOLUTION modifying the March 14, 2020 emergency order relating to residential evictions. Date Notes: Filed with City Clerk: Mayor's Signature: Sponsors: Mosqueda Vetoed by Mayor: Veto Overridden: Veto Sustained: Attachments: Ex A - Emergency Order Issued March 14, 2020, Ex B - Modified Emergency Order v3 Reviewer: Uploaded By: jodee.schwinn@seattle.gov Filing Requirements/Dept Action: History of Legislative File Legal Notice Published: Yes No Ver- Acting Body: Date: Action: Sent To: Due Date: Return Result: sion: Date: City Clerk 03/16/2020 sent for review Council President's Office Action Text: The Resolution (Res) was sent for review. to the Council President's Office Council President's 03/16/2020 sent for review City Council Office Action Text: The Resolution (Res) was sent for review. to the City Council 1 City Council 03/16/2020 referred City Council 1 City Council 03/16/2020 held Pass Action Text: The Motion carried, and the Resolution (Res) was held until after the Executive Sssion by the following vote: Notes: ACTION 1: Motion was made and duly seconded to pass Resolution 31938. ACTION 2: Office of the City Clerk Page 1 Printed on 3/20/2020 Legislative Summary Continued (Res 31938) Motion was made by Councilmember Herbold, duly seconded and carried, to amend Resolution 31938, Exhibit B, Section 1.B, as shown in the underlined language below: Residential or commercial landlord shall not initiate an unlawful detainer action_ issue a notice of termination, or otherwise act on any termination notice, Including any action or notice related to a rental agreement that has expired or will expire during the effective date of this Emergency Order, unless the unlawful detainer action or action on a termination notice is due to actions by the tenant constituting an imminent threat to the health or safety of neighbors, the landlord, or the tenant's or landlord's household members. ACTION 3: Motion was made by Councilmember Mosqueda, duly seconded and carried, to hold Resolution 31938, until after the Executive Session. In Favor: 7 Councilmember Herbold, Councilmember Juarez, Councilmember Lewis, Councilmember Mosqueda, Councilmember Pedersen, Councilmember Sawant, Councilmember Strauss Opposed: 0 1 City Council 03/16/2020 adopted as Pass amended Action Text: The Motion carried, the Resolution (Res) was adopted as amended by the following vote, and the President signed the Resolution: Notes: ACTION 4: Motion was made by Councilmember Lewis, duly seconded and carried, to amend Resolution 31938, Exhibit B, by substituting version 3 for version 2. ACTION 5: Motion was made by Councilmember Mosqueda, duly seconded and carried, to amend Resolution 31938, Section 2.B, as shown in the underlined language below: B. Issuing orders or taking other actions to provide rent relief, including deferred payment of rent, requiring payment plans, and other strategies to assist small businesses and nonprofit organizations who are unable to pay rent or pay their employees due to economic disruptions caused by COVID-19. ACTION 6: Motion was made and duly seconded to adopt Resolution 31938 as amended. In Favor: 7 Councilmember Herbold, Councilmember Juarez, Councilmember Lewis, Councilmember Mosqueda, Councilmember Pedersen, Councilmember Sawant, Councilmember Strauss Office of the City Clerk Page 2 Printed on 3/20/2020 Legislative Summary Continued (Res 31938) Opposed: 0 2 City Clerk 03/16/2020 attested by City Clerk Action Text: The Resolution (Res) was attested by City Clerk. Office of the City Clerk Page 3 Printed on 3/20/2020 CITY OF SEATTLE Resolution (Res): Res 31938 A RESOLUTION modifying the March 14, 2020 emergency order relating to residential evictions. WHEREAS, on February 29, 2020, Washington Governor Jay Inslee declared a state of emergency in response to new cases of COVID-19, directing state agencies to use all resources necessary to prepare for and respond to the outbreak; and WHEREAS, on March 3, 2020 the Mayor proclaimed a civil emergency related to the spread of COVID-19, authorizing the Mayor to exercise the emergency powers necessary for the protection of the public peace, safety, and welfare; and WHEREAS, on March 5, 2020 the Council adopted Resolution 31937 affirming the civil emergency, modifying orders transmitted by the Mayor related to the emergency, and establishing Council's expectations related to future orders and reporting by the Mayor during the civil emergency; and WHEREAS, on March 11, 2020, Washington Governor Jay Inslee amended his emergency order to prohibit gatherings of 250 people or more for social, spiritual and recreational activities including, but not limited to, community, civic, public, leisure, faith-based, or sporting events; parades; concerts; festivals; conventions; fundraisers; and similar activities; and WHEREAS, on March 12, 2020, Washington Governor Jay Inslee announced that all schools in King, Snohomish, and Pierce Counties will close through April 24, 2020; and WHEREAS, on March 12, 2020, Public Health - Seattle and King County confirmed 270 cases of COVID-19, including 27 deaths, in King County; and SEATTLE CITY COUNCIL Page 1 Printed on 3/16/20 File Number: Res 31938 WHEREAS, in light of COVID-19 spreading person-to-person and particularly between people who are in close contact with one another, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) has recommended that: those who are mildly ill self-isolate by staying home, avoiding public areas, and avoiding transportation; sensitive populations avoid people who are sick; and everyone practice self-distancing; and WHEREAS, the Washington State Legislature has declared a state policy to help residents who are experiencing a temporary crisis in retaining stable housing to avoid eviction from their homes, as expressed in Laws of 2019, ch. 356, $ 1; and WHEREAS, the September 2018 Seattle Women's Commission and the King County Bar Association's report Losing Home: The Human Cost of Eviction in Seattle ("Losing Home Report") found that the most disadvantaged groups face the highest likelihood of eviction; and WHEREAS, the Losing Home report found that most evicted respondents became homeless, with 37.5 percent completely unsheltered, 25.0 percent living in a shelter or transitional housing, and 25.0 percent staying with family or friends. Only 12.5 percent of evicted respondents found another apartment or home to move into; and WHEREAS, a 2018 investigation by the King County Medical Examiner's Office found that over half of 107 presumed homeless deaths investigated occurred outside and attributed approximately 121, or 62 percent, of presumed homeless deaths investigated to non-natural causes (drug overdose, accidents (including hypothermia), suicide, homicide, and undetermined), making it clear that people experiencing homelessness have a much higher risk than the general population of developing exposure-related conditions; and WHEREAS, persons with underlying health conditions are at greater risk of fatality if they catch SEATTLE CITY COUNCIL Page 2 Printed on 3/16/20 File Number: Res 31938 COVID-19, and preventing individuals from becoming higher-risk patients will protect the public health, safety, and welfare of the region; and WHEREAS, the impacts of the emerging public health crisis on the economy, employment, job retention, child care, and businesses may result in: workers being unable to go to work because of illness; the need to care for children home from day care or school or for other family members without paid sick or safe time; and reduced hours due to reduced demand, furlough, or unemployment as businesses struggle during the state of emergency. These risks are compounded especially for workers without paid sick or safe time, those in the "gig economy," and others without protections that help stabilize income. Historically disadvantaged populations are already at greater risk of eviction. Compounding existing risk with the impacts from the COVID-19 emergency may increase the likelihood of exposure, spread, and contraction of the virus; and WHEREAS, in the last two weeks there has been a significant drop in the number of tenants appearing in court for their eviction hearings in King County resulting in default judgments being entered and tenant losing substantial rights to assert defenses or access legal and economic assistance; and WHEREAS, providing a moratorium on evictions for certain causes resulting from the COVID-19 pandemic is necessary as an additional step to protect public health to support stable housing, decrease the likelihood that individuals and families will fall into homelessness, enabling tenants in the City whose income and ability to work is affected due to COVID-19 to remain in their homes; and decrease the likelihood that individuals and families will increase the likelihood of exposure for themselves or others due to an eviction while the COVID-19 emergency exists; and WHEREAS, on March 14, 2020 the Mayor issued a civil emergency order related to residential evictions; and SEATTLE CITY COUNCIL Page 3 Printed on 3/16/20 File Number: Res 31938 WHEREAS, Seattle Municipal Code subsection 10.02.020.B provides that the Seattle City Council can either ratify and confirm, modify, or reject such an order; NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED BY THE CITY COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF SEATTLE THAT: Section 1. The Civil Emergency Order relating to residential evictions issued by Mayor Jenny A. Durkan, dated March 14, 2020, attached to this resolution as Exhibit A, is modified, as shown in Exhibit B. Section 2. The Council requests that the Mayor consider issuing additional emergency orders and make expenditures pursuant to the authority assumed in Section 3 of the modified Emergency Proclamation provided in Exhibit B to Resolution 31937, to help workers and businesses impacted by the public health crisis on the economy. Additional orders and expenditures to consider include: A. Increasing funding for programs that provide emergency rental assistance and other financial support to households unable to pay rent due to economic disruptions caused by COVID-19; and B. Issuing orders or taking other actions to provide rent relief, including deferred payment of rent, requiring payment plans, and other strategies to assist small businesses and nonprofit organizations who are unable to pay rent or pay their employees due to economic disruptions caused by COVID-19. Adopted by the City Council the day of 2020, and signed by me in open session in authentication of its adoption this day of 2020. President of the City Council Filed by me this day of 2020. SEATTLE CITY COUNCIL Page 4 Printed on 3/16/20 Exhibit A CIVIL EMERGENCY ORDER CITY OF SEATTLE MORATORIUM ON RESIDENTIAL EVICTIONS WHEREAS, in my capacity as Mayor, I proclaimed a civil emergency exists in the City of Seattle in the Mayoral Proclamation of Civil Emergency dated March 3, 2020; and WHEREAS, the facts stated in that proclamation continue to exist, as well as the following additional facts: WHEREAS, the World Health Organization (WHO) has declared that COVID-19 disease is a global pandemic, which is particularly severe in high risk populations such as people with underlying medical conditions and the elderly, and the WHO has raised the health emergency to the highest level requiring dramatic interventions to disrupt the spread of this disease; and WHEREAS, as of March 13, 2020, Public Health - Seattle &amp; King County announced 58 new cases of COVID-19 in King County residents, for a total of 328 cases, including 32 deaths; and WHEREAS, on March 13, 2020, the Governor of Washington state issued an emergency order announcing all K-12 schools in Washington to be closed from March 17, 2020 through April 24, 2020 to combat the spread of the disease; and WHEREAS, on March 13, 2020, the President of the United States declared a national emergency to allow the government to marshal additional resources to combat the virus; and WHEREAS, on March 11, 2020, the Governor of Washington state and the Local Health Officer for Public Health - Seattle &amp; King County issued parallel orders prohibiting gatherings of 250 people or more for social, spiritual and recreational activities in King County; and WHEREAS, the COVID-19 crisis has had a significant impact on the local economy impacting the retail, restaurant and other industries resulting in layoffs and reduced work hours for a significant percentage of this workforce and loss of income for small businesses; and WHEREAS, layoffs and substantially reduced work hours will lead to widespread economic hardship that will disproportionately impact low- and moderate- income workers resulting in lost wages and the inability to pay for basic household expenses, including rent; and WHEREAS, in the last two weeks there has been a significant 50% drop in the number of tenants appearing in court for their eviction hearings in King County resulting in default judgments being entered and tenants losing substantial rights to assert defenses or access legal and economic assistance; and WHEREAS, evictions result in a loss of housing and create housing instability, potentially increasing the number of people experiencing homelessness and creating a heightened risk of disease transmission; and Civil Emergency Order Moratorium on Evictions Page 1 of 4 Exhibit A WHEREAS, the City invests in eviction prevention programs, but resources are not sufficient to address housing stability needs of dislocated workers during this unprecedented public health epidemic; and WHEREAS, jurisdictions across the nation are considering or have implemented eviction prevention to provide housing stability to dislocated workers during this unprecedented public health emergency; and WHEREAS, Art. XI, Sec. 11 of the Washington State Constitution grants cities like The City of Seattle broad police powers to "make and enforce within its limits all such local police, sanitary and other regulations as are not in conflict with general laws"; and WHEREAS, the Washington State Legislature has declared a state policy to help residents who are experiencing a temporary crisis in retaining stable housing to avoid eviction from their homes, as expressed in Laws of 2019 c 356 section 1; and WHEREAS, a temporary moratorium on residential evictions during the COVID-19 outbreak will protect the public health, safety, and welfare by reducing the number of individuals and families entering into homelessness during this epidemic, which means lowering the number of people who may develop the disease or spread the disease; and WHEREAS, the civil emergency necessitates the utilization of emergency powers granted to the Mayor pursuant to: the Charter of the City of Seattle, Article V, Section 2; Seattle Municipal Code (SMC) Chapter 10.02; and chapter 38.52 RCW; and WHEREAS, SMC 10.02.020.A.15 authorizes the Mayor to proclaim "such other orders as are imminently necessary for the protection of life and property" and take extraordinary measures to protect the public peace, safety and welfare; and WHEREAS, the COVID-19 civil emergency requires the issuance of an order that is specifically aimed at a moratorium on residential evictions during the civil emergency in order to keep people housed and protect the public safety, health and welfare as set forth in this Civil Emergency Order; and WHEREAS, the conditions of this Civil Emergency Order are designed to provide the least necessary restriction on the rights of the public per SMC 10.02.025.C and WHEREAS, pursuant to SMC 10.02.025.B, I believe it is in the best interest of the public safety, rescue and recovery efforts, and the protection of property that the exercise of certain rights be temporarily limited as set forth in this Civil Emergency Order; therefore, BE IT PROCLAIMED BY THE MAYOR OF THE CITY OF SEATTLE, THAT: I, JENNY A. DURKAN, MAYOR OF THE CITY OF SEATTLE, ACTING UNDER THE AUTHORITY OF SEATTLE MUNICIPAL CODE SECTIONS 10.02.020.A.15, AND MY MAYORAL PROCLAMATION OF CIVIL EMERGENCY, DATED MARCH 3, 2020, HEREBY ORDER: Civil Emergency Order Moratorium on Evictions Page 2 of 4 Exhibit A SECTION 1: A. Effective immediately, a moratorium on residential evictions for non-payment is hereby ordered until the earlier of the termination of the civil emergency declared in the Proclamation of Civil Emergency dated March 3, 2020 or 30 days from the effective date of this Emergency Order. The decision to extend the moratorium shall be evaluated and determined by the Mayor based on public health necessity; B. An owner of a housing unit shall not issue a notice of termination or initiate an eviction action for non-payment of rent or otherwise act on a termination notice for non-payment of rent during this moratorium. Further, no late fees or other charges due to late payment of rent shall accrue during the moratorium; and C. For any pending eviction action for the non-payment of rent, it shall be a defense to any eviction action that the eviction of the tenant would occur during the moratorium. Given the public health emergency and public safety issues, a court may grant a continuance for a future hearing date in order for the eviction action to be heard after the moratorium. SECTION 2: All mayoral proclamations and orders presently in effect shall remain in full force and effect except that, insofar as any provision of any such prior proclamation is inconsistent with any provision of this proclamation, then the provision of this proclamation shall control. SECTION 3: A copy of this Civil Emergency Order shall be delivered to the Governor of the State of Washington and to the County Executive of King County. To the extent practicable, a copy of this Civil Emergency Order shall be made available to all news media within the City and to the general public. In order to give the widest dissemination of this Civil Emergency Order to the public, as many other available means as may be practical shall be used, including but not limited to posting on public facilities and public address systems. SMC 10.02.100. SECTION 4: This Civil Emergency Order shall immediately, or as soon as practical, be filed with the City Clerk for presentation to the City Council for ratification and confirmation, modification or rejection, and if rejected this Civil Emergency Order shall be void; however, any such rejection or modification shall not affect any actions previously taken. The Council may, by resolution, ratify, modify or reject the order. If the City Council modifies or rejects this Civil Emergency Order, said modification or rejection shall be prospective only, and shall not affect any actions taken prior to the modification or rejection of this Civil Emergency Order, including the City's responsibility for the actual costs incurred by those who were ordered by or entered into contracts with the City, as set forth in Seattle Municipal Code subsection 10.02.020.B. The Council shall endeavor to act on any order within 48 hours of its being presented to the Council by the Mayor. Civil Emergency Order Moratorium on Evictions Page 3 of 4 Exhibit A DATED this day of 2020, at am/pm. JENNY A. DURKAN MAYOR OF THE CITY OF SEATTLE Civil Emergency Order Moratorium on Evictions Page 4 of 4 Exhibit B - Modified Emergency Order V CIVIL EMERGENCY ORDER CITY OF SEATTLE MORATORIUM ON RESIDENTIAL EVICTIONS WHEREAS, in my capacity as Mayor, I proclaimed a civil emergency exists in the City of Seattle in the Mayoral Proclamation of Civil Emergency dated March 3, 2020; and WHEREAS, the facts stated in that proclamation continue to exist, as well as the following additional facts: WHEREAS, the World Health Organization (WHO) has declared that COVID-19 disease is a global pandemic, which is particularly severe in high risk populations such as people with underlying medical conditions and the elderly, and the WHO has raised the health emergency to the highest level requiring dramatic interventions to disrupt the spread of this disease; and WHEREAS, as of March 13, 2020, Public Health - Seattle &amp; King County announced 58 new cases of COVID-19 in King County residents, for a total of 328 cases, including 32 deaths; and WHEREAS, on March 13, 2020, the Governor of Washington state issued an emergency order announcing all K-12 schools in Washington to be closed from March 17, 2020 through April 24, 2020 to combat the spread of the disease; and WHEREAS, on March 13, 2020, the President of the United States declared a national emergency to allow the government to marshal additional resources to combat the virus; and WHEREAS, on March 11, 2020, the Governor of Washington state and the Local Health Officer for Public Health - Seattle &amp; King County issued parallel orders prohibiting gatherings of 250 people or more for social, spiritual and recreational activities in King County; and WHEREAS, the COVID-19 crisis has had a significant impact on the local economy impacting the retail, restaurant and other industries resulting in layoffs and reduced work hours for a significant percentage of this workforce and loss of income for small businesses; and WHEREAS, layoffs and substantially reduced work hours will lead to widespread economic hardship that will disproportionately impact low- and moderate- income workers resulting in lost wages and the inability to pay for basic household expenses, including rent; and WHEREAS, in the last two weeks there has been a significant 50% drop in the number of tenants appearing in court for their eviction hearings in King County resulting in default judgments being entered and tenants losing substantial rights to assert defenses or access legal and economic assistance; and WHEREAS, evictions result in a loss of housing and create housing instability, potentially increasing the number of people experiencing homelessness and creating a heightened risk of disease transmission; and Civil Emergency Order Moratorium on Evictions Page 1 of 4 Exhibit B - Modified Emergency Order V WHEREAS, the City invests in eviction prevention programs, but resources are not sufficient to address housing stability needs of dislocated workers during this unprecedented public health epidemic; and WHEREAS, jurisdictions across the nation are considering or have implemented eviction prevention to provide housing stability to dislocated workers during this unprecedented public health emergency; and WHEREAS, Art. XI, Sec. 11 of the Washington State Constitution grants cities like The City of Seattle broad police powers to "make and enforce within its limits all such local police, sanitary and other regulations as are not in conflict with general laws"; and WHEREAS, the Washington State Legislature has declared a state policy to help residents who are experiencing a temporary crisis in retaining stable housing to avoid eviction from their homes, as expressed in Laws of 2019 c 356 section 1; and WHEREAS, a temporary moratorium on residential evictions during the COVID-19 outbreak will protect the public health, safety, and welfare by reducing the number of individuals and families entering into homelessness during this epidemic, which means lowering the number of people who may develop the disease or spread the disease; and WHEREAS, the civil emergency necessitates the utilization of emergency powers granted to the Mayor pursuant to: the Charter of the City of Seattle, Article V, Section 2; Seattle Municipal Code (SMC) Chapter 10.02; and chapter 38.52 RCW; and WHEREAS, SMC 10.02.020.A.15 authorizes the Mayor to proclaim "such other orders as are imminently necessary for the protection of life and property" and take extraordinary measures to protect the public peace, safety and welfare; and WHEREAS, the COVID-19 civil emergency requires the issuance of an order that is specifically aimed at a moratorium on residential evictions during the civil emergency in order to keep people housed and protect the public safety, health and welfare as set forth in this Civil Emergency Order; therefore, WHEREAS, the conditions of this Civil Emergency Order are designed to provide the least necessary restriction on the rights of the public per SMC 10.02.025.C and WHEREAS, pursuant to SMC 10.02.025.B, I believe it is in the best interest of the public safety, rescue and recovery efforts, and the protection of property that the exercise of certain rights be temporarily limited as set forth in this Civil Emergency Order; therefore, BE IT PROCLAIMED BY THE MAYOR OF THE CITY OF SEATTLE, THAT: I, JENNY A. DURKAN, MAYOR OF THE CITY OF SEATTLE, ACTING UNDER THE AUTHORITY OF SEATTLE MUNICIPAL CODE SECTIONS 10.02.020.A.15, AND MY Civil Emergency Order Moratorium on Evictions Page 2 of 4 Exhibit B - Modified Emergency Order V3 MAYORAL PROCLAMATION OF CIVIL EMERGENCY, DATED MARCH 3, 2020, HEREBY ORDER: SECTION 1: A. Effective immediately, a moratorium on residential evictions for non-payment is hereby ordered until the earlier of the termination of the civil emergency declared in the Proclamation of Civil Emergency dated March 3, 2020 or 30 60 days from the effective date of this Emergency Order. The decision to extend the moratorium shall be evaluated and determined by the Mayor based on public health necessity; B. An owner of a housing unit residential landlord shall not initiate an unlawful detainer action, issue a notice of termination, or otherwise act on any termination notice, including any action or notice related to a rental agreement that has expired or will expire during the effective date of this Emergency Order, unless the unlawful detainer action or action on a termination notice is due to actions by the tenant constituting an imminent threat to the health or safety of neighbors, the landlord, or the tenant's or landlord's household members issue a notice of termination OF initiate an eviction action for non-payment of rent or otherwise act on a termination notice for nen- payment of rent during this moratorium. Further, no late fees or other charges due to late payment of rent shall accrue during the moratorium; and C. It shall be a defense to any eviction action that the eviction of the tenant will occur during the moratorium, unless the eviction action is due to actions by the tenant constituting an imminent threat to the health or safety of neighbors, the landlord, or the tenant's or landlord's household members. For any pending eviction action, regardless if the tenant has appeared, for the non-payment of rent, it shall be a defense to any eviction action that the eviction of the tenant would occur during the moratorium. Given the public health emergency and public safety issues, court may grant a continuance for a future hearing date in order for the eviction action to be heard after the moratorium a court may grant a continuance for a future court date in order for the matter to heard at a time after the moratorium is terminated; and D. Effective immediately. the Sheriff of King County is requested to cease execution of eviction orders during the moratorium. SECTION 2: All mayoral proclamations and orders presently in effect shall remain in full force and effect except that, insofar as any provision of any such prior proclamation is inconsistent with any provision of this proclamation, then the provision of this proclamation shall control. SECTION 3: A copy of this Civil Emergency Order shall be delivered to the Governor of the State of Washington and to the County Executive of King County. To the extent practicable, a copy of this Civil Emergency Order shall be made available to all news media within the City and to the general public. In order to give the widest dissemination of this Civil Emergency Order to the public, as Civil Emergency Order Moratorium on Evictions Page 3 of 4 Exhibit B - Modified Emergency Order V3 many other available means as may be practical shall be used, including but not limited to posting on public facilities and public address systems. SMC 10.02.100. SECTION 4: This Civil Emergency Order shall immediately, or as soon as practical, be filed with the City Clerk for presentation to the City Council for ratification and confirmation, modification or rejection, and if rejected this Civil Emergency Order shall be void; however, any such rejection or modification shall not affect any actions previously taken. The Council may, by resolution, ratify, modify or reject the order. If the City Council modifies or rejects this Civil Emergency Order, said modification or rejection shall be prospective only, and shall not affect any actions taken prior to the modification or rejection of this Civil Emergency Order, including the City's responsibility for the actual costs incurred by those who were ordered by or entered into contracts with the City, as set forth in Seattle Municipal Code subsection 10.02.020.B. The Council shall endeavor to act on any order within 48 hours of its being presented to the Council by the Mayor. DATED this day of 2020, at am/pm. JENNY A. DURKAN MAYOR OF THE CITY OF SEATTLE Civil Emergency Order Moratorium on Evictions Page 4 of 4 O File Number. Res 31938 Monica Martinez Simmons, City Clerk (Seal) Exhibits: Exhibit A - Emergency Order Issued March 14, 2020 Exhibit B - Modified Emergency Order Adopted by the City Council the 16th day of March, 2020, and signed by me in open session in authentication of its adoption this 16th March day of March, 2020. Smosqueda President of the City Council Teresa Mosqueda, Councilmember Filed by me this 16th day or March , 2020. Monica Martinez Simmons, City Clerk (Seal) SEATTLE CITY COUNCIL Page 5 Printed on 3/16/20</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
