<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/ca/cities/san-jose/emergency-services/proclamations/2020-03-06">
  <num type="Proclamation"/>
  <heading>Proclamation of Local Emergency</heading>
  <heading type="oll">City of San Jose, CA Proclamation of Local Emergency, March 6, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-06</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-06.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-06</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>CITY OF SAN JOSE PROCLAMATION OF LOCAL EMERGENCY WHEREAS, Title 8, Chapter 8.08, Part 2, Section 808.210 of the Municipal Code of the City of San Jose ("City") empowers the Director of the Emergency Services to proclaim the existence or threatened existence of a local emergency when the City is affected or likely to be affected by public calamity and the City Council is not in session; and WHEREAS, the Director of the Emergency Services of the City does hereby find the following: 1 . A novel coronavirus (named "COVID-19") was first detected in Wuhan City, Hubei Province, China, in December 2019. The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) considers the virus to be a very serious public health threat with outcomes ranging from mild sickness to severe illness and death. COVID-19 has spread globally to over 85 countries, infected more than 95,000 people, and killed more than 3,000 individuals. ' 2. On January 24, 2020 the City established and activated its Pandemic Management Team and the City's Pandemic Response Plan at Stage 1, Monitoring. 3 On January 30, 2020, the World Health Organization declared the COVID-19 outbreak a Public Health Emergency of International Concern. On January 31, 2020, the United States Secretary of Health and Human Services declared a Public Health Emergency. 4 On January 31, 2020, the first case of COVID-19 was confirmed in the County of Santa Clara ("County"). 5 On January 31, 2020 the City elevated its response from Pandemic Response Stage 1 to 2. 6. On February 10, 2020, the County declared a local health emergency and proclaimed a local emergency. 7 On February 26, 2020, the third case of COVID-19 was confirmed in the County and the City escalated its Pandemic Response Stage from 2 to 3. 8. By March 4, 2020 the number of confirmed cases of COVID-19 had increased to eleven (11) in the County with confirmed community spread. The California Department of Health Services reported its first death related to COVID-19 and the Governor of California declared a state of emergency. 9. On March 4, 2020, the City partially activated its Emergency Operations Center and began scaling up resources and response in preparation for event and facility closures, increased telecommuting/ work-from-home capacity for employees, augmentation of communication to employees and coordination with partner agencies, as well as other work-place and program modifications to ensure the continuity of City operations while protecting the safety of our employees, providing effective communication, and supporting the County. World Health Organization Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) Situation Report - 45 https://www.who int/docs/default-source/coronaviruse/situation.reports/20200305-sitrep-45-covid-19 pdf?sfursn=ed2ba78b 2 By March 5, 2020, the number of confirmed cases of COVID-19 had increased to twenty (20) in the County, with strong evidence of increasing community spread. The County expanded its guidance and City escalated its Pandemic Response Stage from 3 to 4. WHEREAS, the above facts give rise to conditions of extreme peril to the safety and health of persons within the City. WHEREAS, these conditions are or are likely to be beyond the control of the services, personnel, equipment, and facilities of the City; and WHEREAS, the efforts required to prepare for, respond to, mitigate, and recover from the increasing spread of COVID-19 have and will continue to impose extraordinary requirements and expenses on the City, requiring diversion of resources from day-to-day operations; and WHEREAS, the City Council of the City of San Jose is not in session and cannot immediately be called into session. NOW, THEREFORE, IT IS HEREBY PROCLAIMED that a local emergency now exists throughout the City; and IT IS FURTHER PROCLAIMED AND ORDERED that during the existence of said local emergency, the powers, functions, and duties of the emergency organization of this City shall be those prescribed by state law, by the Charter of this City, by ordinance, and resolutions of this City; and that this emergency proclamation shall expire in seven (7) days after issuance unless confirmed and ratified by the City Council of the City of San Jose. Date: 3/6 / 2020 By D. DSYL David Sykes Director of Emergency Services City of San Jose</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
