<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/ca/cities/long-beach/healthofficer/orders/2020-03-12">
  <num type="Order"/>
  <heading>Order of the Health Officer</heading>
  <heading type="oll">City of Long Beach Order of the Health Officer March 12, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-12</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-12.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="http://www.longbeach.gov/globalassets/health/media-library/documents/diseases-and-condition/information-on/novel-coronavirus/03-12-19-order-of-the-health-officer"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-12</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>CITY OF LONGBEACH Health and Human Services 2525 Grand Avenue, Long Beach, CA 90815 (562) 570-4000 FAX (562) 570-4049 ORDER OF THE HEALTH OFFICER DATE ORDER ISSUED: March 12, 2020 Summary: The virus that causes Coronavirus 2019 Disease is easily transmitted, especially in group settings, and it is essential that the spread of the virus be slowed to protect the ability of public and private health care providers to handle the influx of new patients and safeguard public health and safety. Because of the risk of the rapid spread of the virus, and the need to protect the most vulnerable members of the community, this Order prohibits all public and private indoor and outdoor gatherings within an enclosed space of 250 persons in the City of Long Beach beginning at 12 a.m. on March 13, 2020 and continuing until April 30, 2020, subject to the limited exceptions and under the terms and conditions more particularly set forth below. For all other gatherings, the Health Officer strongly recommends following the social distancing protocols attached to this Order, including canceling, rescheduling, or not attending events that do not allow social distancing of 6 feet per person. Organizations that serve high-risk populations should cancel gatherings of more than 10 people. UNDER THE AUTHORITY OF CALIFORNIA HEALTH AND SAFETY CODE SECTIONS 101040, 101085, AND 120175, THE HEALTH OFFICER OF THE CITY of LONG BEACH ORDERS: 1. Effective as of 12:00 a.m. on Friday, March 13, 2020, and continuing until 11:59 p.m. on April 30, 2020, public or private Mass Gatherings (as defined in Section 8 below) are prohibited in the City of Long Beach (the "City"). 2. In addition, the Health Officer strongly recommends that all persons within the City follow the social distancing outlined in the "Implementation of Mitigation Strategies for Communities with Local COVID-19 Transmission" issued by the United States Centers for Disease Control and Prevention ("CDC") on or around March 11, 2020 (available online at www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/downloads/community-mitigation-strategy.pdf). The Health Officer urges people to (i) not attend non-essential gatherings during the duration of this Order in order to help slow down the spread of the COVID-19 virus; (ii) postpone or cancel smaller gatherings that do not allow for social distancing of 6 feet per person; and (iii) cancel gatherings of more than 10 people if the organization serves high-risk populations, and (iv) large non-essential entertainment or social gatherings should be postponed or canceled. 3. This Order is issued based on evidence of increasing occurrence of Coronavirus Disease 2019 ("COVID-19") within the City and surrounding communities, scientific evidence and best practices regarding the most effective approaches to slow the transmission of communicable diseases generally and COVID-19 specifically, and evidence that the age, condition, and health of a significant portion of the population of the City places them at risk for serious health complications, including death, from COVID-19. The scientific evidence shows that at this stage of the emergency, it is essential to slow virus transmission as much as possible to protect the most vulnerable and to prevent the health care system from being overwhelmed. ORDER OF THE HEALTH OFFICER DATE ORDER ISSUED: March 12, 2020 Page |2 4. This Order will reduce the likelihood that many individuals will be exposed to COVID-19 at a single event and will thereby slow the spread of COVID-19 in our community. By reducing the spread of COVID-19, this Order will help preserve critical and limited healthcare capacity in the City. 5. This Order is issued to prevent circumstances often present in Mass Gatherings that are likely to exacerbate the spread of COVID-19. Those circumstances include, without limitation: (a) the increased likelihood that Mass Gatherings will attract people from a broad geographic area; (b) the prolonged time period during which large numbers of people are in close proximity; (c) the difficulty in tracing exposure when large numbers of people attend a single event; and (d) the inability to ensure that attendees follow adequate hygienic and social distancing practices like those described in the attached Social Distancing Recommendations. 6. This Order is issued in accordance with, and incorporates by reference, the March 4, 2020 Proclamation of a State of Emergency and the March 12, 2020 Executive Order N-25-20 issued by Governor Gavin Newsom, the March 4, 2020 Proclamation by the Acting City Manager Declaring the Existence of a Local Emergency issued by Tom Modica, and the March 4, 2020 Declaration of Local Health Emergency Regarding Novel Coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19) issued by the Health Officer. 7. The Health Officer will continue to assess the quickly evolving situation and may, at any time or from time to time, modify or extend this Order, or issue additional orders, related to COVID-19. 8. Definitions: a. For purposes of this Order, a "Mass Gathering" is any event or convening, subject to the exceptions and clarifications below, that brings together or is likely to bring together 250 or more persons at the same time in a single room or other single confined or indoor space, such as, by way of example and without limitation, an auditorium, theatre, stadium (indoor or outdoor), arena or event center, meeting hall, conference center, or any other confined indoor or confined outdoor space. b. A "Mass Gathering" includes events in confined outdoor spaces, which means an outdoor space that (i) is enclosed by a fence, physical barrier, or other structure and (ii) where people are present, and they are within arm's length of one another for extended periods. c. This Order also does not prohibit gatherings of people in multiple, separate enclosed spaces in a single building such as a multiplex movie theater, so long as 250 people are not present in any single space as the same time. This Order also does not prohibit use of enclosed spaces where 250 or more people may be present at different times during the day, so long as 250 or more people are not present in the space at the same time. For any gathering covered by this subsection c., the Health Officer strongly encourages compliance with the attached Social Distancing Recommendations, including providing hand sanitizer and tissues and increasing cleaning of commonly touched surfaces. ORDER OF THE HEALTH OFFICER DATE ORDER ISSUED: March 12, 2020 Page |3 d. For purposes of clarity, a "Mass Gathering" does not include the following: (i) Long Beach Airport, (ii) public or private schools; (ili) museums (so long as visitors are generally are not within arm's length of one another for extended periods); (iv) spaces where 250 or more persons may be in transit or waiting for transit such as bus, ferry, or subway stations or terminals (or shopping areas associated with the buildings housing those stations or terminals); (v) office space, hotels, or residential buildings; (vi) grocery stores, shopping malls, or other retail establishments where large numbers of people are present but it is unusual for them to be within arm's length of one another for extended periods; and (vii) hospitals and medical facilities. In all such settings, the Health Officer recommends following the attached Social Distancing Recommendations, and harm reduction measures such as hand sanitizer and tissues should be provided when possible. However, except for spaces covered by clause (iv) above, any specific large gathering space that is part of any building included in this subparagraph d. is subject to the prohibition on Mass Gatherings if the space holds 250 or more people. A "Mass Gathering" also includes events held in a cruise ship while that ship is docked at any City port. 9. This Order shall be effective until 12:00 p.m. on April 30, 2020, or until it is earlier rescinded, superseded, or amended by the Health Officer or by the State Public Health Officer, in writing. IT IS SO ORDERED: anissa Davi's Anissa Davis, MD, DrPH, Health Officer, City of Long Beach Date: March 12, 2020</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
