<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/ca/cities/san-diego/mayor/proclamations/2020-03-12">
  <num type="Proclamation"/>
  <heading>Proclamation of Local Emergency</heading>
  <heading type="oll">City of San Diego, CA Proclamation of Local Emergency, March 12, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-02-14</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-12.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-12</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>THE CITY OF SAN SAN DIEGO . STATE OF . VINJOBFIV3 30 City of San Diego PROCLAMATION OF LOCAL EMERGENCY By the Mayor WHEREAS, pursuant to San Diego Municipal Code Section 51.0105(a)(1), the Mayor is authorized to proclaim the existence of a local emergency when the City Council is not in session; and WHEREAS, at the time of this proclamation the City Council has adjourned to their next scheduled session for Monday, March 16, 2020; and WHEREAS, a novel coronavirus, COVID-19, causes infectious disease and was first detected in Wuhan City, Hubei Province, China in December 2019; and WHEREAS, COVID-19 virus symptoms include fever, cough, and shortness of breath; outcomes have ranged from mild to severe illness, and in some cases death; and WHEREAS, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention considers the virus to be a very serious public health threat; and WHEREAS, on January 30, 2020, the World Health Organization declared the outbreak a 'public health emergency of international concern;" and WHERAS, on January 31, 2020, United States Health and Human Services Secretary Alex M. Azar II declared a public health emergency for the United States to aid the nation's healthcare community in responding to COVID-19; and WHEREAS, on February 2, 2020, the federal government initiated the suspension of the entry of foreign nationals who were in China within the past fourteen days. United States citizens, residents, and their immediate family members who were in the Hubei province and other parts of mainland China are screened upon their entry into the United States. Those without symptoms traveling from areas of China (other than Hubei province) are allowed to continue to their final destination, but are requested to self-quarantine in coordination with local public health officials for up to fourteen days. Federal quarantine of some individuals traveling from Wuhan is presently occurring at the Marine Corps Air Station (MCAS) Miramar; and WHEREAS, as of February 14, 2020, there were two confirmed cases of COVID-19 in San Diego County and the San Diego County Public Health Officer has determined that due to the large population and geographic location of San Diego County, combined with the worldwide spread of COVID-19, there is a potential threat of introduction of COVID-19 in San Diego County and declared a Local Health Emergency; and THE CITY OF SA SAN DIEGO . STATE OF City of San Diego PROCLAMATION OF LOCAL EMERGENCY By the Mayor WHEREAS, on February 19, 2020, the County Board of Supervisors ratified the Declaration of Local Health Emergency; and WHEREAS, on March 11, 2020, the World Health Organization declared the COVID-19 outbreak to be a pandemic; and WHEREAS, the presence of the COVID-19 virus presents conditions of extreme peril to the safety of persons within the City of San Diego, and continues to directly affect the safety of persons within the City; and WHEREAS, these conditions warrant and necessitate the proclamation of a local emergency; NOW, THEREFORE, IT IS HEREBY PROCLAIMED that a local emergency currently exists, and has existed since February 14, 2020, in the City of San Diego due to the continued threat of spread of the COVID-19 virus, and shall be deemed to continue to exist for seven days unless ratified by the City Council, and then until its termination is proclaimed by the City Council of the City of San Diego. IT IS FURTHER PROCLAIMED AND REQUESTED that a copy of this proclamation be forwarded to the Governor of California in support of his proclamation that a State of Emergency exists within the City of San Diego. IT IS FURTHER PROCLAIMED AND ORDERED that during the existence of this local emergency, the powers, functions and duties of the Mayor of this City shall be those prescribed by State law and the Charter, ordinances, resolutions and approved plans of the City of San Diego in order to mitigate the effects of this local emergency, including the receipt, processing, and coordination of all inquiries and requirements necessary to obtain available state and federal assistance. Dated: March 2 2020</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
