<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/tx/cities/el-paso/departments/public-health/orders/2020-03-17/1">
  <num type="Order"/>
  <heading>City of El Paso Health Authority Orders for Assisted Living Facilities, Senior Living Facility Settings</heading>
  <heading type="oll">City of El Paso Health Authority Orders for Assisted Living Facilities, Senior Living Facility Settings, March 17, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./1.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-17</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>Department of Public Health MAYOR CITY OF EL PASO HEALTH AUTHORITY ORDERS FOR ASSISTED LIVING FACILITIES, Dee Margo SENIOR LIVING FACILITY SETTINGS CITY COUNCIL March 17, 2020 EFFECTIVE IMMEDIATELY District 1 Peter Svarzbein In lieu of presence of COVID-19 in our community, the Department of Public Health District 2 is issuing the following Health Authority Orders for every assisted living facility, Alexsandra Annello senior living facility and adult day programs in El Paso County: District 3 Implement social distancing measures, e.g.: Cassandra Hernandez o Cancel large gatherings (e.g., group social events with 10 or more people). Alter schedules to reduce mixing (e.g., stagger meal, activity, and District 4 Dr. Sam Morgan arrival/departure times). o Limit programs with external staff. District 5 Isabel Salcido . Daily upon arrival screen attendees/residents for temperature and respiratory District 6 symptoms. Claudia L. Rodriguez Staff should wear masks and wash hands thoroughly before entering and after exit District 7 of room of inhabitants. Henry Rivera . Consider suspension of new admissions to facilities. District 8 . Implement short-term closures as needed (e.g., if COVID-19 cases in staff, residents Cissy Lizarraga or clients who live elsewhere) for cleaning and contact tracing. Implement longer-term closure or quarantine of facility if warranted, until situation CITY MANAGER resolves. Tommy Gonzalez Suspend visitor access but arrange for alternate means for family members to communicate (e.g., staff assist with phone calls or videoconferences with visitors). Exceptions for end-of-life family visits need to be considered, with limited access of visitors to other areas or people in the facility and these patients should be in a different areas to ensure other clients are not exposed to outside guests. Hector I. Ocaranza, M.D., MPH Health Authority City/County of El Paso, TX Robert Resendes - Public Health Director Department of Public Health | 5115 El Paso Dr. | El Paso, TX 79905 EPA O: (915) 212-0200 | Email: ResendesR@elpasotexas.gov TX CITY OF FL PASO DELIVERING EXCEPTIONAL SERVICES</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
