<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/tx/cities/el-paso/departments/public-health/orders/2020-03-17/2">
  <num type="Order"/>
  <heading>City of El Paso Health Authority Orders for for Workplaces in El Paso City-county</heading>
  <heading type="oll">City of El Paso Health Authority Orders for for Workplaces in El Paso City-county, March 17, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-17</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>THE CO TEXAS Department of Public Health MAYOR Dee Margo CITY OF EL PASO HEALTH AUTHORITY ORDERS FOR WORKPLACES IN EL PASO CITY- COUNTY March 17, 2020 CITY COUNCIL EFFECTIVE IMMEDIATELY District 1 In lieu of presence of COVID-19 in El Paso County, the Health Authority for the El Peter Svarzbein Paso City-County is issuing the following Health Authority Orders for Workplaces. District 2 These approaches are used to minimize morbidity and mortality caused by COVID-19 Alexsandra Annello and to minimize social and economic impacts of COVID-19. District 3 Cassandra Hernandez . Postpone non-essential work travel Encourage staff to telework if equipped to do so District 4 Dr. Sam Morgan Expand sick leave policies: Implement extended telework arrangements (when feasible) District 5 Ensure flexible leave policies for staff who need to stay home due to Isabel Salcido school/childcare dismissals and to encourage individuals to stay home if they District 6 are sick Claudia L. Rodriguez . Implement social distancing measures, e.g.: District 7 Space workers at the worksite by 6 Ft. distance from each other Henry Rivera o Stagger work schedules District 8 O Decrease social contacts in the workplace (limit in-person Cissy Lizarraga meetings) O All break areas must accommodate distancing with regular disinfection of all eating surfaces CITY MANAGER Tommy Gonzalez o Eliminate large work-related gatherings (e.g., staff meetings, after-work functions larger than 10 persons) o Cancel work-sponsored conferences, tradeshows, etc . Conduct regular health checks upon arrival each day (e.g., temperature and respiratory symptom screening) of staff and visitors entering buildings Workers with travel from High-risk area (as established by CDC) facilitate work from home or using virtual means and monitor symptoms for 14 days Hector I. Ocaranza, M.D., MPH Health Authority City/County of El Paso, TX Robert Resendes - Public Health Director Department of Public Health | 5115 El Paso Dr. | El Paso, TX 79905 EPA O: (915) 212-0200 | Email: ResendesR@elpasotexas.gov TX CITY OF EL PASO DELIVERING EXCEPTIONAL SERVICES</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
