<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/tx/cities/el-paso/departments/public-health/orders/2020-03-17/3">
  <num type="Order"/>
  <heading>Orders for Daycare (adult and Children) in El Paso City-county</heading>
  <heading type="oll">Orders for Daycare (adult and Children) in El Paso City-county, March 17, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./3.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-17</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>CITY OFEL Department of Public Health MAYOR ORDERS FOR DAYCARE (ADULT AND CHILDREN) SETTINGS IN EL PASO CITY- Dee Margo COUNTY March 17, 2020 CITY COUNCIL In lieu of the current state of emergency due to the presence of the coronavirus COVID-19 in District 1 Peter Svarzbein our community, the City of El Paso Department of Public Health (DPH) is issuing the following Health Authority Orders for Daycare Settings: District 2 Alexsandra Annello Staff and Attendees: District 3 . Identify daycare workers over the age of 60 with serious chronic medical Cassandra Hernandez conditions and assign them to areas with minimal exposure to visitors and District 4 attendees. Dr. Sam Morgan Monitor staff and attendees upon arrival and departure for possible signs District 5 and symptoms of COVID-19 such as: Isabel Salcido o fever greater than 100F, District 6 o cough, Claudia L. Rodriguez o shortness of breath. District 7 Any symptomatic staff or attendee should be dismissed until they are fever Henry Rivera free without medications for &gt;24 hrs and have no cough. District 8 Isolate any symptomatic attendee until picked-up by parent. Cissy Lizarraga . Attendance should be prohibited to any staff/attendee who: o Is a confirmed case of COVID-19 until cleared by City of El Paso Department of Public Health CITY MANAGER Tommy Gonzalez o In the previous 14 days has had contact with someone with a confirmed diagnosis of COVID-19; o is under investigation for COVID-19; or o In the previous 14 days has travelled internationally to countries with widespread, sustained community transmission. Daycare Operations: No more than 20 attendees per room will be allowed at the same time. . Lunches should be programmed and staggered to prevent crowding in lunchroom. Robert Resendes - Public Health Director Department of Public Health | 5115 El Paso Dr. | El Paso, TX 79905 EPA O: (915) 212-0200 | Email: ResendesR@elpasotexas.gov TXV CITY OF EL PASO DELIVERING EXCEPTIONAL SERVICES THEC CITY OF Department of Public Health MAYOR Dee Margo . Ensure that each attendee is provided individual meals and snacks. Do not serve family style meals. . Prohibit any person except the following from accessing an operation: CITY COUNCIL o operation staff. District 1 persons with legal authority to enter, including law enforcement Peter Svarzbein officers, HHSC Attendee Care Licensing staff, and Department of District 2 Family and Protective Services staff Alexsandra Annello professionals providing services to attendees O attendees enrolled at the operation and District 3 Cassandra Hernandez o parents or legal guardians who have attendees enrolled and present at the operation. District 4 Dr. Sam Morgan Require pickup and drop-off of attendees outside of the operation, unless it's determined that there is a legitimate need for the parent to enter an District 5 Isabel Salcido operation. . No more than 1 parent, guardian or designee can pick up or drop off an District 6 attendee. Claudia L. Rodriguez Make water and soap available to perform frequent handwashing during the District 7 day. Henry Rivera . Review and improve current cleaning practices of your daycare setting. District 8 Make available and visible COVID-19 prevention print materials in your Cissy Lizarraga daycare. CITY MANAGER The proposed orders are to be effective immediately and publicly disseminated Tommy Gonzalez around the city and county of El Paso, Texas. Hector I. Ocaranza, M.D., MPH. Health Authority City/County of El Paso, TX Robert Resendes - Public Health Director Department of Public Health | 5115 El Paso Dr. | El Paso, TX 79905 EPA O: (915) 212-0200 | Email: ResendesR@elpasotexas.gov TXV CITY DP EL PASO DELIVERING EXCEPTIONAL SERVICES</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
