<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/tx/cities/el-paso/departments/public-health/orders/2020-03-17/4">
  <num type="Order"/>
  <heading>Health Authority COVID-19 Prevention Orders for El Paso City-county</heading>
  <heading type="oll">Health Authority COVID-19 Prevention Orders for El Paso City-county, March 17, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./4.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-17</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>Department of Public Health Health Authority COVID-19 Prevention Orders for El Paso City- County MAYOR Dee Margo March 17, 2020 Due to COVID-19's presence in El Paso County, the City of El Paso Department of Public CITY COUNCIL Health Public Health Authority is issuing temporary orders to mitigate and slow down the District 1 spread of the disease in El Paso City-County. These approaches are believed to be Peter Svarzbein necessary to preserve health and well-being of our community members and to protect District 2 the ability of public and private health care providers to handle the influx of new patients Alexsandra Annello and safeguard public health and safety. District 3 Cassandra Hernandez Social distancing is proven to be essential part of the control measure against a respiratory illness such as COVID-19. We understand the social and economic impact of this order, District 4 but it is believed to be a necessary action to take. Dr. Sam Morgan District 5 This order is to be Effective as of Tuesday, March 17, 2020 effective immediately and Isabel Salcido continuing until April 1, 2020 at 08:00 am MST. District 6 Claudia L. Rodriguez Bars, lounges, taverns, arcades and night clubs shall close. District 7 Restaurants shall limit the amount of people on their premises at one time to half of Henry Rivera their designated seating maximum occupancy and ensure tables are at least 6ft apart District 8 from each other. Cissy Lizarraga Restaurants shall disinfect and sanitize commonly touched surfaces and non-food contact surfaces at least once every hour. CITY MANAGER . Restaurants shall not allow parties of more than 6 people in one table. Tommy Gonzalez Restaurants with a bar(s) (no more than 50% of sales derived from alcohol) must discontinue the use of the bar section to minimize close contact of patrons. Tables within bar area have to be spaced a minimum of 6 ft between tables and have to serve food. Discourage long stays at restaurants establishments. Robert Resendes - Public Health Director Department of Public Health | 5115 El Paso Dr. | El Paso, TX 79905 EPA O: (915) 212-0200 | Email: ResendesR@elpasotexas.gov TX CITY OF EL PASO DELIVERING EXCEPTIONAL SERVICES Department of Public Health Restaurants must adopt and implement a screening policy for food handlers and all MAYOR employees, and establish protocols for employee exclusion if they develop the Dee Margo following symptoms: " Fever of greater than 100OF CITY COUNCIL Cough and shortness of breath District 1 . Make available and visible COVID-19 prevention print materials in your business Peter Svarzbein District 2 Alexsandra Annello District 3 Cassandra Hernandez District 4 Hector I. Ocaranza, M.D., MPH Dr. Sam Morgan Health Authority City/County of El Paso, TX District 5 Isabel Salcido District 6 Claudia L. Rodriguez District 7 Henry Rivera District 8 Cissy Lizarraga CITY MANAGER Tommy Gonzalez Robert Resendes - Public Health Director Department of Public Health | 5115 El Paso Dr. | El Paso, TX 79905 EPA O: (915) 212-0200 | Email: ResendesR@elpasotexas.gov TX CITY OF EL PASO DELIVERING EXCEPTIONAL SERVICES</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
