<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Atlanta Executive Order" id="us/ga/cities/atlanta/mayor/orders/2020-03-16">
  <num type="Order">2020-007</num>
  <heading>Declaring a State of Emergency and Directing That There Be a Temporary Prohibition on Large Public Assemblages, Events or Gatherings of More than 50 People Until March 31, 2020.</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-16</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-16.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-16</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>Executive Order Office of the Mayor I EPK City of Atlanta 2020 MAR 16 PM 6:44 EXECUTIVE ORDER NUMBER 2620-07 BY THE MAYOR DECLARING A STATE OF EMERGENCY AND DIRECTING THAT THERE BE A TEMPORARY PROHIBITION ON LARGE PUBLIC ASSEMBLAGES, EVENTS, OR GATHERINGS OF MORE THAN 50 PEOPLE WITHIN THE CITY OF ATLANTA THROUGH MARCH 31, 2020 IN RESPONSE TO THE COVID-19 PANDEMIC CRISIS. WHEREAS, pursuant to Section 2-181(a) of the Code of the City of Atlanta ("City"), the Mayor, as chief executive of the City, shall have the emergency power to declare an emergency to exist when, in the mayor's opinion, there is an extreme likelihood of destruction of life or property due to an unusual conditions; and WHEREAS, pursuant to Section 2-181(b) of the Code of the City of Atlanta, the Mayor, as chief executive of the City, shall have the right to exercise any or all of the following options after such declaration of emergency: (1) To use employees of the city other than employees of the department of police to assist in the safety and preservation of life, limb and property of the citizenry of the city. (2) To close streets and sidewalks and to delineate areas within the city wherein an emergency exists. (3) To impose emergency curfew regulations. (4) To close business establishments within the affected area. (5) To close any and all city-owned buildings and other facilities to the use of the general public. (6) To do any and all acts necessary and incidental to the preservation of life, limb and property of the citizenry of the city. WHEREAS, no emergency power as set forth in this section may be effective for more than 72 hours after the declaration of an emergency. WHEREAS, pursuant to Section 2-182 of the Code of the City of Atlanta, the Mayor may issue executive orders which apply to events of short duration and which expire at the next meeting of the City Council subsequent thereof unless ratified by a majority vote of the members present and voting; and WHEREAS, COVID-19 is a new and contagious disease caused by a novel coronavirus, that has not previously been seen in humans, which commonly causes upper-respiratory tract illnesses; and Page 1 of 2 WHEREAS, the world has experienced a deep humanitarian crisis with more than 120,000 cases and more than 4,000 deaths due to the COVID-19; and WHEREAS, COVID-19 is officially a global pandemic according to the World Health Organization ("WHO"); and WHEREAS, President Trump has declared a national emergency for the United States of America in response to COVID-19, including banning travel to all European nations; and WHEREAS, Governor Brian Kemp declared a public health emergency in the state of Georgia as of March 14, 2020 due to COVID-19; and WHEREAS, as of March 14, 2020, Georgia now has 66 confirmed cases of COVID-19 and one COVID-19 related death; and WHEREAS, the Center for Disease Control "(CDC") has issued guidance on the emerging and rapidly evolving situation of the COVID-19 pandemic, including how to protect oneself from this illness; and WHEREAS, social distancing is recommended by the CDC to prevent the continued spreading of this illness in the community; and WHEREAS, Dallas, Pittsburgh, Washington, New York, and California have all banned large gatherings in public places in response to the COVID-19 pandemic; and WHEREAS, it is in the best interest of the public and the City to ban any large public gathering of 250 or more persons in public places during the COVID-19 pandemic to reduce the potential catastrophic impact of the COVID-19 pandemic per CDC guidelines; and NOW THEREFORE, I, KEISHA LANCE BOTTOMS, AS MAYOR OF THE CITY OF ATLANTA, NOW HEREBY AUTHORIZE, ORDER AND DIRECT AS FOLLOWS: As of March 2020, declare that there exists a state of emergency within the City of Atlanta due to the COVID-19 pandemic and that all public assemblages, events, and gatherings of 50 or more persons be prohibited within the City and territorial limits of the City of Atlanta until through March 31, 2020. The City shall take such actions as may be necessary to implement this order. This order shall remain in effect only for the time stated herewith and is not intended to, and does not, create any right or benefit, substantive or procedural, enforceable at law or in equity by any party against the City of Atlanta, its departments, agencies, or entities, its officers, employees, or agents, or any other person. This ith day of March, 2020. ATTESTED: Municipal Clerk Page 2 of 2 Foris Webb, III Municipal Clerk</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
