<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/ca/cities/stockton/city-manager/orders/2020-03-12">
  <num type="Proclamation"/>
  <heading>Proclamation of the Existence of a Local Emergency</heading>
  <heading type="oll">City of Stockton Proclamation of the Existence of a Local Emergency, March 12, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-12</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-12.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="http://stocktonca.gov/files/2020_03_12_SignedProclamation_ExistenceLocalEmergency.pdf"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-12</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>CITY OF STOCKTON PROCLAMATION OF THE EXISTENCE OF A LOCAL EMERGENCY The Stockton Municipal Code at section 2.82.060 empowers the Director of Emergency Services/City Manager to proclaim the existence or threatened existence of a local emergency when the City is affected by a public calamity and the City Council is not in session: and The City Manager acting as the Director of Emergency Services, does hereby find that: 1 . Conditions of extreme peril to the safety of persons and property have arisen within the City of Stockton, caused by the serious public health threat presented by the presence and continued transmission of the novel coronavirus (COVID - 19) commencing on or about 12:00 p.m. on the 12th day of March, 2020: and 2. The City Council of the City of Stockton is not in session and cannot immediately be called into session. NOW, THEREFORE, IT IS HEREBY PROCLAIMED AND ORDERED that during the existence of said local emergency the powers, functions, and duties of the emergency organization of this City shall be those prescribed by state law, ordinances and resolutions of this City, and by the City of Stockton Emergency Plan. Dated and time: March 12, 2020, 11:00 a.m. the BOX HARRY BLACK, City Manager/ Director of Emergency Services ATTEST: TON FOUNDED JU ELIZA GARZARCHY CHE 90 # 6181 AND PoemDeck of the City of Stockton</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
