<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Sacramento Resolution" id="us/ca/cities/sacramento/mayor/orders/2020-03-13">
  <num type="Resolution">2020-0075</num>
  <heading>A Resolution Declaring the Existence of a Local Emergency Relating to the COVID-19 Pandemic</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-03-13</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-13.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="http://records.cityofsacramento.org/ViewDoc.aspx?ID=s6tFBnt4W+IDK+VTAxwLOqmrf2gfpry4"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-13</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>RESOLUTION NO. 2020-0075 Adopted by the Sacramento City Council March 13, 2020 A Resolution Declaring the Existence of a Local Emergency Relating to the COVID-19 Pandemic BACKGROUND A. The City of Sacramento is responding to the spread of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), a respiratory illness first identified in Wuhan, Hubei Province, China, and now being reported internationally, including in the United States. B. On January 31, 2020, the Federal Health and Human Services Secretary declared a public health emergency to aid the nation's healthcare community in responding to the outbreak of COVID-19 in the United States. C. On March 4, 2020, Governor Gavin Newsom proclaimed a State of Emergency as a result of the threat of COVID-19 in the State of California. On March 11, 2020, the World Health Organization characterized the COVID-19 outbreak as a pandemic. E. As of March 12, 2020, the Word Health Organization reported a total of 125,048 confirmed cases of COVID-19 and 4,613 deaths globally; the Center for Disease Control, reported a total of 1,215 cases and 36 deaths in the United States; the California Department of Public Health reported a total of 198 cases and 4 deaths in the State; and the County of Sacramento reported a total of 17 cases and 1 death in the county. Federal, State and local public health agencies agree that the number of cases of COVID-19 will significantly increase in all regions of the country, including the City of Sacramento. This increasing problem may dramatically impact City staff and the City's ability to provide essential services. F. On March 12, 2020, Governor Gavin Newsom, issued Executive Order N-25-20. The Governor stated, among other things, that despite sustained efforts, COVID-19 remains a threat and further efforts are needed to control the spread of the virus; that local officials may issue guidance limiting or recommending limitations upon attendance at public assemblies, conferences, or other mass events; and that individuals exposed to COVID-19 may be unable to work, may experience a loss of income, health care, medical coverage, and the ability to pay for housing and basic needs. The Governor ordered, among other things, that residents are to heed orders of state and local health Resolution 2020-0075 March 13, 2020 Page 1 of 4 officials, including social distancing measures; and that provisions of state law relating to disability insurance, unemployment insurance, emergency medical services, taxes, medical facilities, and public meetings, are modified during this emergency. G. Sacramento City Code chapter 2.116 empowers the City Council to proclaim the existence of a local emergency under certain conditions. H. The COVID-19 pandemic has caused, and will continue to cause, conditions of extreme peril to persons within the City of Sacramento that are likely to be beyond the control of services, personnel, equipment, and facilities of the city, requiring the combined forces of other political subdivisions to combat. These conditions warrant and necessitate the proclamation of the existence of a local emergency. BASED ON THE FACTS SET FORTH IN THE BACKGROUND, THE CITY COUNCIL RESOLVES AS FOLLOWS: Section 1. The City Council finds and determines that the background statements A through I are true. Section 2. The City Council declares that a local emergency now exists throughout the City of Sacramento, California and shall continue to exist for 30 days, unless terminated earlier by the City Council. This declaration shall be reviewed as required under Sacramento City Code section 2. 116.060. Section 3. City Manager Howard Chan is the director of emergency services, pursuant to Sacramento City Code section 2.116.050. Section 4. If the director of emergency services is unavailable to attend meetings or otherwise perform his duties during an emergency, the director designates Assistant City Manager Chris Conlin to succeed him. If both the director of emergency services and Chris Conlin are unavailable, the director designates Director of Emergency Management Daniel Bowers to succeed them. Section 5. Assistant City Manager Chris Conlin is hereby designated as the authorized City representative for public and individual assistance, for receipt, possession and coordination of all inquiries and requirements necessary to obtain available State and Federal assistance. If Chris Conlin is unavailable, the Director of Emergency Management Daniel Bowers is designated to succeed him. Resolution 2020-0075 March 13, 2020 Page 2 of 4 Section 6. During the local emergency, the powers, functions, and duties of the emergency organization of the City of Sacramento shall be those prescribed by State law, Sacramento City Charter, ordinances and resolutions of the City of Sacramento, and by the City of Sacramento's approved Emergency Operations Plan. Section 7. The City Manager and the City Attorney are directed to do the following: (a) Cancel city permits for special events that more than 250 people may attend and that are scheduled within the next 30 to 60 days, and refund the permit fees upon cancellation. (b) Establish a multi-year operating project (102003000) and transfer $1,000,000 from general fund balance to establish a $1,000,000 economic relief package for small local businesses like restaurants, retail, and day care providers. The package is to include a program to issue zero-interest loans up to $25,000 based on demonstrated need and the establishment of a small-business hotline. Eligible businesses must have written sick leave policies to assist workers impacted by the COVID-19 pandemic. (c) Allow free metered parking after 4:30 p.m. on weekdays and all day on weekends for up to 30 days. (d) Support the school districts in their efforts to ensure that if schools close, children and families can continue to get the food they need. (e) Implement by March 20, 2020 all legal options available to the City to prohibit the eviction of renters that are economically impacted by the COVID-19 pandemic, such as through the use of an eviction moratorium, and report back to Council. Transfer $250,000 from general fund balance to spend up to $250,000 to purchase and distribute emergency sanitation and cleaning supplies and hand-washing stations to facilities that provide services to the homeless. (g) Help acquire and distribute sanitation and cleaning supplies to impacted businesses. (h) Work with the Sacramento Central Labor Council to assist impacted workers dealing with unemployment, paid family leave, disability insurance, unemployment insurance, paid sick leave, and workers compensation. Resolution 2020-0075 March 13, 2020 Page 3 of 4 Section 8. Notwithstanding any provision of the Sacramento City Code to the contrary, the city manager, as the director of emergency services, in addition to the authority granted in Section 7(b), is authorized, without complying with the competitive bidding procedures of title 3 of the Sacramento City Code, to execute any agreement, subject to approval as to form by the city attorney, if the amount of the expenditure or income is less than $250,000 and the agreement is related to emergency response needs. Section 9. A copy of this Resolution shall be forwarded to the State Director of Emergency Services with a request that it be found acceptable in accordance with the provisions of the California Disaster Assistance Act (Cal. Gov. Code $8680 et seq.) Adopted by the City of Sacramento City Council on March 13, 2020, by the following vote: Ayes: Members Ashby, Guerra, Hansen, Harris, Jennings, Schenirer, Warren and Mayor Steinberg Noes: None Abstain: None Absent: Member Carr Attest: Digitally signed by Mindy Cuppy Mindy Cuppy Date: 2020.03.17 13:28:07 -0700 Mindy Cuppy, City Clerk The presence of an electronic signature certifies that the foregoing is a true and correct copy as approved by the Sacramento City Council. Resolution 2020-0075 March 13, 2020 Page 4 of 4</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
