<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Fort Worth Ordinance" id="us/tx/cities/fort-worth/council/ordinances/2020-03-19">
  <num type="General Consent">M&amp;C 20-0188</num>
  <heading>An Ordinance Increasing Estimated Receipts and Appropriations in the Grants Operating Other Fund, in the Amount up to $1,000,000.00, for the Purpose of Interim Funding for Disaster Assistance for COVID-19; Providing for a Severability Clause; Making This Ordinance Cumulative of Prior Ordinances; Repealing All Ordinances in Conflict Herewith; and Providing an Effective Date.</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-03-19</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-19.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://fortworthgov.legistar.com/LegislationDetail.aspx?From=Alert&amp;ID=4396847&amp;GUID=627AD713-D5E4-4199-B890-BC5BDBDAFA0D&amp;Options=ID|Text|&amp;Search=COVID-19"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-19</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>Ordinance No. AN ORDINANCE INCREASING ESTIMATED RECEIPTS AND APPROPRIATIONS IN THE GRANTS OPERATING OTHER FUND, IN THE AMOUNT UP TO $1,000,000.00, FOR THE PURPOSE OF INTERIM FUNDING FOR DISASTER ASSISTANCE FOR COVID-19; PROVIDING FOR A SEVERABILITY CLAUSE; MAKING THIS ORDINANCE CUMULATIVE OF PRIOR ORDINANCES; REPEALING ALL ORDINANCES IN CONFLICT HEREWITH; AND PROVIDING AN EFFECTIVE DATE. BE IT ORDAINED BY THE CITY COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF FORT WORTH, TEXAS: SECTION 1. That in addition to those amounts allocated to the various City departments for Fiscal Year 2020 in the Budget of the City Manager, there shall also be increased estimated receipts and appropriations in the Grants Operating Other Fund, in the amount up to $1,000,000.00, for the purpose of providing interim funding for disaster assistance for COVID-19. SECTION 2. That should any portion, section or part of a section of this ordinance be declared invalid, inoperative or void for any reason by a court of competent jurisdiction, such decision, opinion or judgment shall in no way impair the remaining portions, sections, or parts of sections of this ordinance, which said remaining provisions shall be and remain in full force and effect. SECTION 3. That this ordinance shall be cumulative of Ordinance 23835-09-2019 and all other ordinances and appropriations amending the same except in those instances where the provisions of this ordinance are in direct conflict with such other ordinances and appropriations, in which instance said conflicting provisions of said prior ordinances and appropriations are hereby expressly repealed. SECTION 4. This ordinance shall take effect upon adoption. APPROVED AS TO FORM AND LEGALITY: ECRETARY Assistant City Attorney Mary J. Kayser ADOPTED AND EFFECTIVE:</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
