<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Sacramento Ordinance" id="us/ca/cities/sacramento/council/ordinances/2020-03-17">
  <num type="Ordinance">2020-0015</num>
  <heading>An Ordinance Relating to a Temporary Moratorium on Evicting Tenants and Declaring the Ordinance to Be an Emergency Measure to Take Effect Immediately</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-17.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="http://records.cityofsacramento.org/ViewDoc.aspx?ID=s6tFBnt4W+J00gzaaFKwtP9Vpq1YxZQU"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-17</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>ORDINANCE NO. 2020-0015 Adopted by the Sacramento City Council March 17, 2020 An Ordinance Relating to a Temporary Moratorium on Evicting Tenants and Declaring the Ordinance to be an Emergency Measure to Take Effect Immediately Upon Adoption BE IT ENACTED BY THE COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF SACRAMENTO: SECTION 1. Findings. The City Council finds and declares as follows: A. On March 4, 2020, the Governor declared a State of Emergency in California due to the threat of Coronavirus Disease 2019 ("COVID-19"). On March 5, 2020, the Sacramento County Public Health Officer declared a public health emergency in Sacramento County due to COVID-19. Due to directives from federal, state, and local health officials, residents have been advised to avoid public gatherings and stay at home to prevent the spread of this disease. B. On March 16, 2020, the Governor issued Executive Order N-28-20. The order suspends any state law that would preempt or otherwise restrict the city's exercise of its police power to impose substantive limitations on evictions based on nonpayment of rent resulting from the impacts of COVID-19. C. The city has been impacted by the health crisis of this global pandemic. Sporting events, concerts, plays, and conferences have been cancelled. School closures have occurred and may continue. Employees have been advised to work at home. As a result, restaurant and retail business has significantly declined and workers have been impacted by lost wages and layoffs. Parents have had to miss work to care for home-bound school-age children. As the virus spreads, workers may have to stay home for extended periods. D. Many tenants have experienced sudden income loss, and further income impacts are anticipated. The loss of wages caused by the effects of COVID-19 may impact tenants' ability to pay rent when due, leaving tenants vulnerable to eviction. E. Providing tenants with a short-term protection from eviction due to the inability to pay rent will help avoid increasing the homeless population and stabilize the rental housing market by reducing displacement. F. During this state of emergency, and in the interests of protecting the public health and preventing transmission of the coronavirus, it is essential to avoid unnecessary displacement of tenants. Prohibiting evictions on a temporary basis is needed until the spread of the virus can be minimized and the emergency restrictions lifted. Ordinance 2020-0015 March 17, 2020 Page 1 of 3 G. Nothing in this ordinance waives a tenant's obligations to pay back rent owed once this ordinance is no longer effective. SECTION 2. Moratorium on evictions due to nonpayment of rent during the COVID-19 emergency. A. This Section 2 remains in effect until the expiration of the Governor's Executive Order N-28-20, including any extensions. B. This ordinance applies to all residential, but not commercial, tenants. C. No landlord shall endeavor to evict a tenant for nonpayment of rent if the tenant, in accordance with Section 2, demonstrates that the inability to pay rent is due to the Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19), the state of emergency regarding COVID-19, or following government-recommended COVID-19 precautions. D. As used in this Section 2, "covered reason for delayed payment" means a tenant's loss of income due to any of the following: (a) tenant was sick with COVID-19 or caring for a household or family member who is sick with COVID-19; (b) tenant experienced a lay-off, loss of hours, or other income reduction resulting from COVID-19 or the state of emergency; (c) tenant's compliance with a recommendation from a government agency to stay home, self-quarantine, or avoid congregating with others during the state of emergency; and (d) tenant's need to miss work to care for a home-bound school-age child. E. To take advantage of the protections afforded under this ordinance, a tenant must do all the following: a. Notify the landlord in writing before the day rent is due that the tenant has a covered reason for delayed payment; b. Provide the landlord with verifiable documentation to support the assertion of a covered reason for delayed payment; and c. Pay the portion of rent that the tenant is able to pay. F. If a tenant complies with the requirements of this ordinance, a landlord shall not serve a notice pursuant to California Code of Civil Procedure sections 1161 and 1162, file or prosecute an unlawful detainer action based on a three-day pay or quit notice, or otherwise endeavor to evict the tenant for nonpayment of rent. G. Nothing in this ordinance relieves the tenant of liability for the unpaid rent after expiration of this ordinance. Ordinance 2020-0015 March 17, 2020 Page 2 of 3 SECTION 3. Effective Date. This ordinance takes effect immediately upon enactment. SECTION 4. 120-Day Payback Period. Tenants who were afforded eviction protection under Section 2 of this ordinance shall have up to 120 days after the expiration of the Governor's Executive Order N-28-20, including any extensions, to pay their landlord all unpaid rent. During that 120-day period, the protections against eviction found in Section 2 of this ordinance apply for such tenants. SECTION 5. Emergency Declaration. The city council declares this ordinance to be an emergency measure, to take effect immediately upon adoption pursuant to Sacramento City Charter section 32(g)(2). The facts constituting the emergency are as follows: The directives from health officials to contain the spread of COVID-19 has resulted in loss of business, furloughs, loss of wages, and lack of work for employees. To protect the public health, safety, and welfare, the city must act to prevent eviction of tenants who are unable to pay rent due to wage losses caused by the effects of COVID-19. An emergency measure is necessary to protect tenants from eviction for a temporary period. Adopted by the City of Sacramento City Council on March 17, 2020, by the following vote: Ayes: Members Ashby, Carr, Guerra, Hansen, Harris, Jennings, Schenirer, Warren and Mayor Steinberg Noes: None Abstain: None Absent: None Attest: Mindy Cuppy Digitally signed by Mindy Cuppy Date: 2020.03.19 13:42:01-07'00' Mindy Cuppy, City Clerk The presence of an electronic signature certifies that the foregoing is a true and correct copy as approved by the Sacramento City Council. Passed for Publication: Not applicable Published: To be published in its entirety Effective: March 17, 2020 Ordinance 2020-0015 March 17, 2020 Page 3 of 3</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
