<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Sacramento Ordinance" id="us/ca/cities/sacramento/council/ordinances/2020-03-17a">
  <num type="Ordinance">2020-0014</num>
  <heading>An Interim Ordinance for One Year Tolling Land Use Entitlements in the City of Sacramento and Declaring the Ordinance to Be an Emergency Measure to Take Effect Immediately upon Adoption</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-17a.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="http://records.cityofsacramento.org/ViewDoc.aspx?ID=s6tFBnt4W+L8+sdZ+fCmqyAatu5raTWJ"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-17</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>ORDINANCE NO. 2020-0014 Adopted by the Sacramento City Council March 17, 2020 An Interim Ordinance for One Year Tolling Land Use Entitlements in the City of Sacramento and Declaring the Ordinance to be an Emergency Measure to Take Effect Immediately Upon Adoption BE IT ENACTED BY THE COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF SACRAMENTO: SECTION 1. Findings. The City Council finds and declares as follows: A. The City of Sacramento is responding to the spread of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), a respiratory illness first identified in Wuhan, Hubei Province, China, and now being reported internationally, including in the United States. B. On January 31, 2020, the Federal Health and Human Services Secretary declared a public health emergency to aid the nation's healthcare community in responding to the outbreak of COVID-19 in the United States. C. On March 4, 2020, Governor Gavin Newsom proclaimed a State of Emergency as a result of the threat of COVID-19 in the State of California. D. On March 11, 2020, the World Health Organization characterized the COVID-19 outbreak as a pandemic. E. As of March 12, 2020, the Word Health Organization reported a total of 125,048 confirmed cases of COVID-19 and 4,613 deaths globally; the Center for Disease Control, reported a total of 1,215 cases and 36 deaths in the United States; the California Department of Public Health reported a total of 198 cases and 4 deaths in the State; and the County of Sacramento reported a total of 17 cases and 1 death in the county. Federal, State and local public health agencies agree that the number of cases of COVID-19 will significantly increase in all regions of the country, including the City of Sacramento. This increasing problem may dramatically impact city staff and the city's ability to provide essential services. F. On March 12, 2020, Governor Gavin Newsom, issued Executive Order N-25-20. The Governor stated, among other things, that despite sustained efforts, COVID-19 remains a threat and further efforts are needed to control the spread of the virus; that local officials may issue guidance limiting or recommending limitations upon attendance at public assemblies, conferences, or other mass events; and that individuals exposed to COVID-19 may be unable Ordinance 2020-0014 March 17, 2020 Page 1 of 3 to work, may experience a loss of income, health care, medical coverage, and the ability to pay for housing and basic needs. The Governor ordered, among other things, that residents are to heed orders of state and local health officials, including social distancing measures; and that provisions of state law relating to disability insurance, unemployment insurance, emergency medical services, taxes, medical facilities, and public meetings, are modified during this emergency. G. On March 13, 2020, the City Council adopted a resolution declaring a local emergency relating to the Covid-19 pandemic. H. These conditions warrant and necessitate measures to mitigate adverse economic effects that may be experienced by businesses and property owners during this emergency. 1. The city council of the City of Sacramento finds and declares that the global health emergency caused by the Coronavirus (COVID-19) outbreak is delaying the start and completion of construction of land development projects and the land use approvals for these projects are at risk of expiring. Because the processing, approval, and issuance of land use entitlements represent a substantial investment of money, time, and effort toward the successful completion of these projects, expiration of these entitlements represents a significant loss for the owners and the city. The city council desires to protect against this potential loss and preserve development opportunities by granting additional time to the term of these entitlements. SECTION 2. Tolling. Notwithstanding the provisions of Title 17 of the Sacramento City Code, the time to establish a use, construct a development project, or demolish a building or structure under a discretionary permit under section 17.808.400, including any extensions thereof, does not include the period that this ordinance is in effect. This section applies only to those entitlements that are valid and not expired as of the effective date of this ordinance. SECTION 3. Interim Ordinance. This ordinance is enacted by the city council as an interim ordinance, without notice and hearing before the Planning and Design Commission and City Council as otherwise required by Title 17. It is anticipated that the economic conditions that are impacting land development will improve within one year. This ordinance remains in effect for one year, after which time it expires and is of no further force or effect. Ordinance 2020-0014 March 17, 2020 Page 2 of 3 SECTION 4. Emergency Declaration. The city council declares this ordinance to be an emergency measure, to take effect immediately upon its adoption pursuant to Sacramento City Charter section 32(g)(2). The facts constituting the emergency are set forth in Section 1, above. Adopted by the City of Sacramento City Council on March 17, 2020, by the following vote: Ayes: Members Ashby, Carr, Guerra, Hansen, Harris, Jennings, Schenirer, Warren and Mayor Steinberg Noes: None Abstain: None Absent: None Attest: Mindy Cuppy Digitally signed by Mindy Cuppy Date: 2020.03.18 11:32:21 -07'00' Mindy Cuppy, City Clerk The presence of an electronic signature certifies that the foregoing is a true and correct copy as approved by the Sacramento City Council. Passed for Publication: Not applicable Published: To be published in its entirety Effective: March 17, 2020 Ordinance 2020-0014 March 17, 2020 Page 3 of 3</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
