<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/ca/cities/riverside/director-of-emergency-services/orders/2020-03-18">
  <num type="Order"/>
  <heading>Order of the Director of Emergency Services Regarding Restaurants and Bars</heading>
  <heading type="oll">City of Riverside Order of the Director of Emergency Services Regarding Restaurants and Bars March 18, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-18</effective>
    <expiration>2020-03-31</expiration>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-18.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://aquarius.riversideca.gov/clerkdb/PDF/lnukpbkyu3apuvegsp1slgjb/2/Order%20-%20Restaurants%20and%20Bars.pdf"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-18</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>CITY OF RIVERSIDE N STATE OF CALIFORNIA w ORDER OF THE DIRECTOR OF EMERGENCY SERVICES A WHEREAS, Government Code section 8634 empowers the Director of Emergency Services to promulgate orders and regulations necessary to provide for the protection of life and property; and WHEREAS, Riverside Municipal Code section 9.20.050 empowers the Director of Emergency Services to do the following: 10 A. During the existence of a "state of war emergency," or the proclaimed existence of a 11 "state of emergency" or a "local emergency" affecting the City to: 12 1. Control and direct the effort of the City Emergency Organization. 13 2. Direct cooperation and coordination of services and staff of the City Emergency 14 Organization and resolve questions of authority and responsibility that may arise between them. 15 3. Represent the City in all dealings with public or private agencies on matters 16 pertaining to emergencies. 17 4. Make and issue rules and regulations on matters reasonably related to the protection 18 of life and property as affected by such emergency. 19 5. Obtain vital supplies, equipment, and such other properties found lacking and 20 required for the protection of life and property and to bind the City for the fair value thereof and, 21 if required immediately, to commandeer the same for public use. 22 6. Require emergency services of any City officer or employee and to command the aid 23 of as many citizens of the community as he or she deems necessary in the execution of his or her 24 duties. 25 7. Requisition necessary personnel or material of any City department or agency. 26 8. Execute all of his or her ordinary power as City Manager, all of the special powers 27 conferred upon him or her by the Riverside Municipal Code, City Council Resolution, City 28 Council approved Emergency Plan, powers conferred upon him or her by any statute, City CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE Council approved agreement, or other lawful authority. 3900 MAIN STREET RIVERSIDE CA 9252 (951) 824-5367 NOW, THEREFORE, IT IS HEREBY PROCLAIMED AND ORDERED by the N Director of Emergency Services of the City of Riverside that in order to slow down the spread of COVID-19 to people and individuals within the City of Riverside, all bars, breweries and wineries in the City of Riverside, except for those that provide food, are hereby closed. Within the parameters of the Order of the Health Officer of the County of Riverside, dated March 16, 2020, inclusive of restrictions on gatherings, all restaurants and cafes within the City of Riverside should not exceed 50% of occupancy and shall adhere to six (6) foot social distancing. Further, should a restaurant contain a bar, restaurant patrons eating food may order from the bar until 10:00 p.m., at which time the bar must close. This order shall continue until March 31, 10 2020, at which time this order will be reconsidered by the City Council. 11 12 Dated : 3/18/2020 Director of Emergency Services 13 City of Riverside 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 On ATforNY's Omar 300 MAIN STREET LIVERSION, CA $3512 (961) 836-5367</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
