<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/tx/cities/dallas/regulations/emergency/2020-03-13">
  <num type="Emergency Regulations"/>
  <heading>Emergency Regulations</heading>
  <heading type="oll">City of Dallas, TX Emergency Regulation, March 13, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-13</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-13.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-13</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>200438 31473 EMERGENCY REGULATIONS WHEREAS, by proclamation issued March 12, 2020, the Mayor declared a state of disaster for the City of Dallas resulting from the COVID-19 Pandemic; and WHEREAS, Section 14B-7 of the Dallas City Code authorizes the City Manager to 'promulgate such regulations as he or she deems necessary to protect life and property and preserve critical resources" while a state of disaster is in effect; NOW, THEREFORE, the following regulations shall take effect immediately upon issuance, and shall continue until the regulations are rescinded, superseded, or amended. or until expiration pursuant to applicable law: SECTION 1. PROHIBITED GATHERINGS. Public or private Community Gatherings (as defined in Section 3 below) are prohibited anywhere in the City of Dallas. SECTION 2. REPORTING OF COVID-19 TESTS. (a) All public, private and commercial laboratories operating within the City of Dallas and performing COVID-19 testing shall report by 5:00 p.m. each day for the prior 24-hour period (1) the number of COVID-19 tests performed and (2) the number of positive COVID-19 tests to Rocky Vaz, Director of Emergency Management for the City of Dallas at Oemdepartment@dallascityhall.com. ( b ) Such laboratories shall not provide names or other individually identifiable health information that could be used to identify an individual patient. This information will be used solely for public health purposes to monitor the testing conducted in the City and mitigate and contain the spread of COVID-19. EMERGENCY REGULATIONS - Page 1 SECTION 3. DEFINITIONS. a. For purposes of these regulations, a "Community Gathering" is any indoor or outdoor event or convening, subject to the exceptions and clarifications below, that brings together or is likely to bring together five-hundred (500) or more persons at the same time in a single room or other single confined or enclosed space, such as an auditorium, theatre, stadium (indoor or outdoor), arena or event center, meeting hall, conference center, large cafeteria, or any other confined indoor or confined outdoor space. b. An outdoor "Community Gathering" under these regulations is limited to events in confined outdoor spaces, which means an outdoor space that (i) is enclosed by a fence, physical barrier, or other structure and (ii) where people are present and they are within arm's length of one another for extended periods. C. These regulations also do not prohibit gatherings of people in multiple, separate enclosed spaces in a single building such as a multiplex movie theater, school or office tower, so long as 500 people are not present in any single space at the same time. These regulations also do not prohibit the use of enclosed spaces where 500 or more people may be present at different times during the day, so long as 500 or more people are not present in the space at the same time. d. For purposes of clarity, a "Community Gathering" does not include the following so long as visitors are generally not within arm's length of one another for extended periods: (i) spaces where 500 or more persons may be in transit or waiting for transit such as airports, bus stations, or terminals; (ii) office space or residential buildings; (iii) grocery stores, shopping malls, or other retail establishments where large numbers of people are present, but it is unusual for them to be within arm's length of one another for extended periods; and (iv) hospitals and medical facilities. EMERGENCY REGULATIONS - Page 2 SECTION 4. POSTING OF THESE REGULATIONS. The owner, manager, or operator of any facility that is likely to be impacted by these regulations shall post a copy of these regulations onsite and visible to users of the facility and provide a copy to any user of the facility asking for a copy. SECTION 5. SEVERABILITY. If any subsection, sentence, clause, phrase, or word of these regulations or any application of them to any person, structure, gathering, or circumstance is held to be invalid or unconstitutional by a decision of a court of competent jurisdiction, then such decision will not affect the validity of the remaining portions or applications of these regulations. SECTION 6. EFFECTIVE IMMEDIATELY. These regulations shall be effective immediately, and continue until they are either rescinded, superseded, or amended or until they expire pursuant to applicable law. SECTION 7. SUSPENSION AND MODIFICATION OF ORDINANCES. (a) Any ordinances or regulations that would prevent temporary sheltering and housing by the City, State of Texas, or the Federal Government in response to the declared disaster are suspended or modified as necessary to make these regulations effective. (b) Any ordinances or regulations that conflict with these regulations are suspended or modified as necessary to make these regulations effective. (c) Suspension or modification of the ordinances and regulations shall remain in effect until these regulations are terminated or until the state of disaster is terminated, whichever is sooner. SECTION 8. PENALTIES. (a) These regulations shall have the effect of ordinances when duly filed with the city secretary. EMERGENCY REGULATIONS - Page 3 (b) A person who violates any provision of these regulation, upon conviction, is punishable by a fine of not less that $50 and not more than $2000. APPROVED AS TO FORM: CHRISTOPHER J. CASO, Interim City Attorney CITY OF DALLAS BY BY: Assistant City Attorney City Manager PASSED : MAR 1 3 2020 EMERGENCY REGULATIONS - Page 4</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
