<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Austin, TX RES. NO." id="us/tx/cities/austin/resolutions/20200312-074">
  <num type="Resolution">20200312-074</num>
  <heading/>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-03-06</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./20200312-074.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-12</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>RESOLUTION NO. 20200312-074 WHEREAS, on March 6, 2020, Mayor Steve Adler, acting in accordance with authority granted to him under the Charter and under Section 418.108(a) of the Texas Government Code, declared a local state of disaster for the City due to concerns related to the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) (the "disaster declaration"); and WHEREAS, Section 418.108(b) of the Texas Government Code provides that such a declaration of disaster may not be continued for a period of more than seven days except with the consent of the governing body of the political subdivision; and WHEREAS, the conditions necessitating the disaster declaration will continue to exist for a period of more than seven days; and WHEREAS, the City Council supports the disaster declaration signed by Mayor Steve Adler on March 6, 2020, and consents to its continuation for a period of more than seven days; NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED BY THE CITY COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF AUSTIN: The City Council hereby ratifies the disaster declaration signed by Mayor Steve Adler on March 6, 2020, and consents to its continuation indefinitely, or until such time as it is terminated by order of the Council. ADOPTED: March 12 , 2020 ATTEST: Frilma Brady for Jannette S. Goodall City Clerk Page 1 of 1</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
