<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/tx/cities/austin/mayor/orders/2020-03-17">
  <num type="Order"/>
  <heading/>
  <heading type="oll">City of Austin, TX Order by the Mayor, March 17, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration>2020-05-01</expiration>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-17.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-17</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>ORDER BY THE MAYOR OF THE CITY OF AUSTIN OCC RECEIVED AT MAR 17 '20 AMG:27 Whereas, on March 6, 2020, a Declaration of Local Disaster was issued to allow the City of Austin to take measures to reduce the possibility of exposure to COVID-19 and promote the health and safety of Austin residents; and Whereas, on March 13, 2020, a Declaration of State of Disaster was issued by Governor Abbott to take additional steps to prepare for, respond to, and mitigate the spread of COVID-19 to protect the health and welfare of Texans; and Whereas, the COVID-19 virus is contagious and spreads through person-to-person contact, especially in group settings; and Whereas, on March 15, 2020, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention ("CDC") recommended that organizers (whether groups or individuals) cancel or postpone in-person events that consist of 50 people or more throughout the United States; and Whereas, on March 16, 2020, President Trump acknowledged the gravity of the COVID- 19 pandemic, releasing strict new guidelines to limit people's interactions, including that Americans should avoid groups of more than 10 people; and Whereas, due to the substantial risks to the public, this Order prohibits Community Gatherings of 10 persons or more anywhere in the City of Austin beginning at 12:00 p.m. (noon) by an earlier Order. on Tuesday, March 17, 2020, and continuing until May 1, 2020, unless terminated or modified NOW THEREFORE, I, MAYOR OF THE CITY OF AUSTIN, PURSUANT TO THE AUTHORITY VESTED BY TEXAS GOVERNMENT CODE CHAPTER 418, HEREBY FIND AND ORDER: SECTION 1. That the findings and recitations set out in the preamble to this ORDER are found to be true and correct and they are hereby adopted by the Mayor and made a part hereof for all purposes. That this Order rescinds and replaces the prior Order issued on March 14, 2020 SECTION 2. Effective as of 12:00 p.m. (noon) on Tuesday, March 17, 2020, and continuing until May 1, 2020, unless terminated or modified by an earlier Order, the Mayor of the City of Austin, Texas, deems it in the public interest to PROHIBIT any public or private Community Gatherings (as defined in Section 3, below) anywhere in the City of Austin. SECTION 3. Definitions: a. For purposes of this Order, a "Community Gathering" is any indoor or outdoor event or convening, subject to the exceptions and clarifications below, that brings together or is likely to bring together ten (10) or more persons at the same time in a single room or space. For clarity, this includes, but is not limited to, weddings, religious services, parties, funerals, sporting events, social events, conferences, and other gatherings. b. This Order does not prohibit gatherings of people in multiple, separate enclosed spaces (including separate cubicles) in a single building such as school classrooms or different floors of a multi-level office, residential building, or hotel, so long as 10 people are not present in any single space at the same time. This Order also does not prohibit the use of enclosed spaces where 10 or more people may be present at different times during the day, so long as 10 or more people are not present in the space at the same time. For any gathering covered by this subsection, the Mayor of the City of Austin and the Austin/Travis County Health Authority strongly encourage compliance with the attached Recommendations, which include social distancing, providing hand sanitizer and tissues, and increasing cleaning of commonly and frequently touched surfaces. c. This Order does not apply to the following: (i) critical infrastructure, including airport facilities and operations, transit, and transit facilities; government buildings providing essential services; schools or institutes of higher learning; (iv) ( v) grocery stores and pharmacies; and hospitals and medical offices and facilities. For purposes of this Order, "grocery stores" includes warehouse stores, big- box stores, bodegas, gas stations, farmers' markets, or food pantries that provide or sell food products or household staples. In these settings, the Mayor of the City of Austin and the Austin/Travis County Health Authority strongly encourage compliance with the attached Recommendations, which include social distancing, providing hand sanitizer and tissues, and increasing cleaning of commonly and frequently touched surfaces. SECTION 4: Our community's critical infrastructure, which includes communications, emergency services, energy, transportation systems, and water and wastewater systems, are ORDERED to continue operating and encouraged to implement screening precautions to protect employees. SECTION 5: Food establishments are ORDERED to close common dining areas open to the public until May 1, 2020, and encouraged to provide take-away or no-contact delivery food service designed to limit exposure between individuals. SECTION 6: The holder of a wine and beer retailer's permit or mixed beverage permit (collectively "bar") is ORDERED to close common bar spaces open to the public and is PROHIBITED from allowing consumption on the bar premises until May 1, 2020. SECTION 7: The City of Austin SUSPENDS all deadlines imposed by City Code, ordinance, rule, or other regulation until May 1, 2020. SECTION 8: That peace officers, City of Austin Code Department inspectors, and the Office of the Austin Fire Marshal, are hereby authorized to enforce this order. Persons who violate this Order violate Austin City Code section 2-6-24. A violation is a misdemeanor punishable by a fine not to exceed $1,000 or confinement in jail for a term not to exceed 180 days. SECTION 9: The Austin Public Health Department will post this Order on its website. In addition, the owner, manager, or operator of any facility that is likely to be impacted by this Order is strongly encouraged to post a copy of this Order onsite and to provide a copy to any member of the public asking for a copy. If any subsection, sentence, clause, phrase, or word of this Order or any application of it to any person, structure, gathering, or circumstance is held to be invalid or unconstitutional by a decision of a court of competent jurisdiction, then such decision will not affect the validity of the remainder of this Order and its application. ORDERED this the 17th day of March, 2020, in the City of Austin, Travis County, Texas, in witness whereof I subscribe my name and cause to be affixed the seal of the City of Austin. Filed with me, the City Clerk of the City of Austin, this 17th day of March, 2020, by Mayor Steve Adler, whose signature I hereby attest under my hand and the seal of the City of Austin. City Clerk ....... A OUNTY TRAVIS CO Austin/Travis County Health Authority Recommendations I) Vulnerable Populations: Limit Outings . Vulnerable populations include people who: o Are 60 years old and older; or o Have certain health conditions such as heart disease, lung disease, diabetes, kidney disease, Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS), and weakened immune systems. .. For vulnerable populations, don't go to gatherings (of 10 people or more) unless it is essential. If you can telecommute, you should. Avoid people who are sick. 2) Workplace and Businesses: Minimize Exposure . Suspend nonessential employee travel. . Minimize the number of employees working within arm's length of one another, including minimizing or canceling large in-person meetings and conferences. Urge employees to stay home when they are sick and maximize flexibility in sick leave benefits. Permit sick employees to stay home without providing a doctor's note. Consider use of telecommuting options. 3) Allowable Events . Cancel or postpone all gatherings. . Do not attend any events or gatherings if sick. For events that aren't cancelled, we recommend: o Having hand washing capabilities, hand sanitizers, and tissues available; o Frequently cleaning high-touch surface areas like countertops, doorknobs, and handrails; and o Finding ways to create physical space to minimize close contact as much as possible. 4) Critical Infrastructure Facilities . Employees who work in and around critical infrastructure should refrain from reporting to work when falling within any of the following criteria: Are sick; 0 Have a fever greater than 99.6 F; o Have had contact with an individual diagnosed with COVID-19; or o Have traveled internationally to countries with travel warnings since February 1, 2020. . If an employee that meets any of the above criteria reports to work, the employer should bar the employee from entering the workplace. An employee that has come in contact with persons exhibiting symptoms associated with COVID-19 or has traveled to an area the World Health Organization or Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) considers a "Hotspot," is expected to follow the initial self- quarantine recommendations. Employers should require employees (either those exhibiting symptoms or all employees) undergo non-invasive temperature readings prior to entering a critical infrastructure facility. Employees refusing to submit to a temperature reading and those with a temperature greater than 99.6 F should be turned away and barred entry into the critical infrastructure facility. Supervisors at critical infrastructure facilities should be authorized to direct employees to return home if the employee is exhibiting symptoms and presenting a threat of infecting other employees at the critical infrastructure facility. Human Resources departments at critical infrastructure facilities are encouraged to create alternate work plans to help employees remain productive while keeping the workforce safe and healthy. 5) Government Buildings Providing Essential Services All nonessential employees should use telecommuting options. . . . Minimize the number of employees working within arm's length of one another. Provide hand washing capabilities, hand sanitizers, and tissues. Frequently clean high-touch surface areas like countertops, doorknobs, and handrails. 6) Schools: Safety First . Do not have your child attend school if sick. . If you have a child with chronic health conditions, consult the child's doctor about school attendance. Frequent re-education of students and staff regarding personal hygiene measures (handwashing, etc.) and ensuring that appropriate signs are posted. Schools should equip all classrooms with hand sanitizers and tissues. Recommend rescheduling or cancelling medium to large events that are not essential, even if the events would otherwise comply with the Order. Explore remote teaching and online options to continue learning. Schools should develop a plan for citywide school closures and families should prepare accordingly. 7) Grocery Stores and Pharmacies . Increase the use and capability of drive-thru, curbside, or delivery services. . Limit or restrict the number of customers permitted in a store at one time. Minimize the number of employees working within arm's length of one another. Provide hand washing capabilities, hand sanitizers, and tissues. Frequently clean high-touch surface areas like countertops, doorknobs, and handrails.</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
