<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/tx/cities/austin/mayor/orders/2020-03-14">
  <num type="Order"/>
  <heading/>
  <heading type="oll">City of Austin, TX Order by the Mayor, March 14, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-15</effective>
    <expiration>2020-05-01</expiration>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-14.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-14</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>ORDER BY THE MAYOR OF THE CITY OF AUSTIN OCC RECEIVED AT MAR 14'20 PM6:33 Whereas, on March 6, 2020, a Declaration of Local Disaster was issued to allow the City of Austin to take measures to reduce the possibility of exposure to COVID-19 and promote the health and safety of Austin residents; and Whereas, on March 13, 2020, a Declaration of State of Disaster was issued by Governor Abbott to take additional steps to prepare for, respond to, and mitigate the spread of COVID-19 to protect the health and welfare of Texans; and Whereas, the COVID-19 virus is contagious and spreads through person-to-person contact, especially in group settings; and Whereas, the Centers on Disease Control and Prevention ("CDC") recommends an "All of Community" approach focused on slowing the transmission of COVID-19 through social distancing to reduce illness and death, while minimizing social and economic impacts; and Whereas, due to the substantial risks to the public, this Order prohibits Community Gatherings of 250 persons or more anywhere in the City of Austin beginning at 2:00 a.m. on March 15, 2020, and continuing until May 1, 2020, unless terminated or modified by an earlier Order; and Whereas, the Austin/Travis County Health Authority recommends following the social distancing protocols attached to this Order, including cancelling, postponing, or not attending events or community gatherings with more than 125 people. In addition, the Austin/Travis County Health Authority urges individuals who are at the highest risk from COVID-19, as determined and defined by the CDC, to not attend and to avoid community gatherings or events that will have or will likely have 10 or more people. NOW THEREFORE, I, MAYOR OF THE CITY OF AUSTIN, PURSUANT TO THE AUTHORITY VESTED BY TEXAS GOVERNMENT CODE CHAPTER 418, HEREBY FIND AND ORDER: SECTION 1. That the findings and recitations set out in the preamble to this ORDER are found to be true and correct and they are hereby adopted by the Mayor and made a part hereof for all purposes. SECTION 2. Effective as of 2:00 a.m. on Sunday, March 15, 2020, and continuing until May 1, 2020, unless terminated or modified by an earlier Order, the Mayor of the City of Austin, Texas, deems it in the public interest to PROHIBIT any public or private Community Gatherings (as defined in Section 3, below) anywhere in the City of Austin. SECTION 3. Definitions: a. For purposes of this Order, a "Community Gathering" is any indoor or outdoor event or convening subject to the exceptions and clarifications below, that brings together or is likely to bring together two-hundred and fifty (250) or more persons at the same time in a single room or other single confined or enclosed space, such as an auditorium, theatre, stadium (indoor or outdoor), arena or event center, meeting hall, conference center, large cafeteria, restaurant, or nightclub/bar, or any other confined indoor or confined outdoor space. For clarity, this includes, but is not limited to, weddings, religious gatherings, parties, funerals, sporting events, social events, conferences, and other large gatherings. . An outdoor "Community Gathering" under this Order is limited to events in confined outdoor spaces, which means an outdoor space that (i) is enclosed by a fence, physical barrier, or other structure and (ii) where people are present and they are within arm's length of one another for extended periods. C. This Order also does not prohibit gatherings of people in multiple, separate enclosed spaces (including separate cubicles) in a single building such as a multiplex movie theater, school classrooms, or different floors of a multi- level building, so long as 250 people are not present in any single space at the same time. This Order also does not prohibit the use of enclosed spaces where 250 or more people may be present at different times during the day, so long as 250 or more people are not present in the space at the same time. For any gathering covered by this subsection c., the Mayor of the City of Austin and the Austin/Travis County Health Authority strongly encourages compliance with the attached Social Distancing Recommendations, including providing hand sanitizer and tissues and increasing cleaning of commonly and frequently touched services. d. For purposes of clarity, a "Community Gathering" does not include spaces where 250 or more persons may be in transit on buses, trains or airplanes; or waiting for transit, such as airports, bus stops or terminals. In addition, 'Community Gathering" does not include the following spaces where 250 or more persons may congregate, so long as visitors are generally not within arm's length of one another for extended periods: (ii) office space or residential buildings; grocery stores, shopping malls, or other retail establishments where large numbers of people may be present, but it is unusual for them to be within arm's length of one another for extended periods; and (iii) hospitals and medical offices and facilities. In all such settings, the Mayor of the City of Austin and the Austin Travis County Health Authority recommends following the attached Social Distancing Recommendations, and personal hygiene measures, including providing hand sanitizer and facial tissues. SECTION 4: That peace officers, City of Austin Code Department inspectors, and the Office of the Austin Fire Marshall, are hereby authorized to enforce this order. Persons who violate this Order violate Austin City Code section 2-6-24. A violation is a misdemeanor punishable by a fine not to exceed $1,000 or confinement in jail for a term not to exceed 180 days. SECTION 5: The Austin Public Health Department will post this Order on its website. In addition, the owner, manager, or operator of any facility that is likely to be impacted by this Order is strongly encouraged to post a copy of this Order onsite and to provide a copy to any member of the public asking for a copy. If any subsection, sentence, clause, phrase, or word of this Order or any application of it to any person, structure, gathering, or circumstance is held to be invalid or unconstitutional by a decision of a court of competent jurisdiction, then such decision will not affect the validity ORDERED this the 14th day of March, 2020, in the City of Austin, Travis County, Texas, in witness whereof I subscribe my name and cause to be affixed the seal of the City of Austin. Filed with me, the City Clerk of the City of Austin, this 14th day of March, 2020, by Mayor Steve Adler, whose signature I hereby attest under my hand and the seal of the City of Austin. City Clerk TRAVIS COL UNTY Austin/Travis County Health Authority Social Distancing Recommendations 1) Vulnerable Populations: Limit Outings . Vulnerable populations include people who are: o0 years old and older; or People with certain health conditions such as heart disease, lung disease, diabetes, kidney disease, and weakened immune systems. For vulnerable populations, don't go to gatherings (of 10 people or more) unless it is essential. If you can telecommute, you should. Avoid people who are sick. 2) Workplace and Businesses: Minimize Exposure . Suspend nonessential employee travel. Minimize the number of employees working within arm's length of one another, including minimizing or canceling large in-person meetings and conferences. Urge employees to stay home when they are sick and maximize flexibility in sick leave benefits. Permit sick employees to stay home without providing a doctor's note. . Consider use of telecommuting options. Some people need to be at work to provide essential services of great benefit to the community. They can take steps in their workplace to minimize risk. 3) Large Gatherings: Cancel Non-essential Events . Recommend cancelling or postponing large gatherings, such as concerts, sporting events, conventions or large community events. Do not attend any events or gatherings if sick. For events that aren't cancelled, we recommend: o Having hand washing capabilities, hand sanitizers, and tissues available; o Frequently cleaning high-touch surface areas like countertops, doorknobs, and handrails; and O Finding ways to create physical space to minimize close contact as much as possible. 4) Schools: Safety First . Do not have your child attend school if sick. . If you have a child with chronic health conditions, consult the child's doctor about school attendance Frequent re-education of students and staff regarding personal hygiene measures (handwashing, etc.) and ensuring that appropriate signs are posted. Schools should equip all classrooms with hand sanitizers and tissues. Recommend rescheduling or cancelling medium to large events that are not essential, even if the events would otherwise comply with the Order. Explore remote teaching and online options to continue learning. Schools should develop a plan for citywide school closures and families should prepare.</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
