<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix=" " id="us/tx/cities/dallas/mayor/proclamations/2020-03-12">
  <num type="Proclamation"/>
  <heading>Proclamation Declaring a Local State of Disaster</heading>
  <heading type="oll">City of Dallas, TX Proclamation Declaring a Local State of Disaster, March 12, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-12</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-12.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-12</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>CITY OF RECEIVED TEXAS 2020 HAR 12 PM 10: 44 CITY SECRETARY OFFICE OF DALLAS MAYOR ERIC JOHNSON LAS. TEXAS PROCLAMATION DECLARING A LOCAL STATE OF DISASTER BE IT REMEMBERED: WHEREAS, in December 2019, a novel coronavirus, now designated COVID-19, was detected in Wuhan, China; and WHEREAS, symptoms of COVID-19 include fever, cough, and shortness of breath, and outcomes have ranged from mild to severe illness and in some cases death; and WHEREAS, on January 30, 2020, the World Health Organization Director General declared the outbreak of COVID-19 as a Public Health Emergency of International Concern and advised countries to prepare for the containment, including active surveillance, early detection, isolation and case management, contact tracing, and prevention of onward spread of the disease; and WHEREAS, on March 5, 2020, the World Health Organization Director General urged aggressive preparedness and activation of emergency plans to aggressively change the trajectory of this epidemic; and WHEREAS, on March 11, 2020, the World Health Organization declared COVID-19 a worldwide pandemic; and WHEREAS, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention is closely monitoring the growing number of COVID-19 cases that have spread into the United States; and WHEREAS, over 1,663 cases of COVID-19 have been reported in the United States, including 40 deaths; and WHEREAS, a large gathering of unidentifiable individuals without necessary mitigation for the spread of infection may pose a risk of the spread of infectious disease; and WHEREAS, unless the actions as hereby provided are immediately initiated, avoidable serious illness and deaths could occur; and WHEREAS, COVID-19 spreads between people who are in close contact with one another through respiratory droplets produced when an infected person coughs or sneezes; and OFFICE OF THE MAYOR CITY HALL 1500 MARILLA ST., 5EN DALLAS, TEXAS 75201 TELEPHONE 214.670.3301 WHEREAS, the continued worldwide spread of COVID-19 presents an imminent threat of widespread illness, which requires emergency action; and WHEREAS, the Dallas City Code defines a disaster as the occurrence or imminent threat of widespread or severe damage, injury, or loss of life or property resulting from any natural cause or man-made cause; and WHEREAS, a man-made cause under the Dallas City Code includes an epidemic or other health emergency; and WHEREAS, a declaration of local disaster includes the ability to take measures to reduce the possibility of exposure to disease and mitigate the risk to, and promote the health and safety of, the residents of the City of Dallas; and WHEREAS, the measures identified in this Proclamation are designed to prevent deaths in the City of Dallas; and WHEREAS, the identification of "community spread" cases of COVID-19 in the City of Dallas and the region could potentially signal that transmission of the virus may no longer be limited to travel to outbreak areas or contact with travelers who have visited outbreak areas. NOW, THEREFORE, by virtue of the authority vested in me by the Dallas City Charter, as the presiding officer of the governing body, the City Council of the City of Dallas, a home-rule city, municipal corporation, body politic and political subdivision of the State of Texas situated in Dallas County, Texas, and pursuant to Section 14B-6 of the Dallas City Code and Section 418.108 of the Texas Government Code (Texas Disaster Act), BE IT PROCLAIMED BY THE MAYOR OF THE CITY OF DALLAS: Section 1. Declaration of Local State of Disaster. A local state of disaster due to this health emergency is hereby declared by the Mayor of the City of Dallas, pursuant to Section 418.108 of the Texas Disaster Act. Section 2. Duration of Local State of Disaster. Pursuant to Section 418.108(b) of the Texas Disaster Act, the local state of disaster due to this health emergency issued in this Proclamation shall continue until revoked, but in no event will it exceed a period longer than seven (7) days of the date hereof, unless continued or renewed by the consent of the City Council of the City of Dallas. Section 3. Publicity and Filing. Pursuant to Section 418.108(c) of the Texas Disaster Act, this declaration of a local state of disaster due to this health emergency shall be given prompt and general publicity and shall be filed promptly with the City Secretary. 2 Section 4. Activation of the City Emergency Management Plan. Pursuant to Section 418.108(d) of the Texas Disaster Act, this declaration of a local state of disaster due to this health emergency activates the City of Dallas Emergency Management Plan. Section 5. Temporary Housing and Emergency Shelter. Pursuant to Section 418.020(d) of the Texas Disaster Act, the City of Dallas is authorized to: (1) temporarily or permanently acquire by lease, purchase, or other means sites required for installation of temporary housing units or emergency shelters for disaster victims; and (2) enter into arrangements necessary to prepare or equip the sites to use the housing units or shelters, including arrangements for the purchase of temporary housing units or shelters and the payment of transportation charges. Section 6. Protective Control Measures and Facilities. Pursuant to Section 122.006 of the Texas Health and Safety Code, the City of Dallas is authorized to adopt rules to protect the health of persons in the City of Dallas, including quarantine rules to protect its residents against communicable disease and provide for the establishment of quarantine stations, emergency hospitals, and other hospitals. Section 7. Reporting of COVID-19 Testing. Pursuant to Chapter 14B-7 of the Dallas City Code, the city manager shall establish an order that all public, private, and commercial labs within the City of Dallas shall report the number of COVID-19 tests conducted on a daily basis to the City of Dallas and establish a penalty for failure to report. Section 8. Limits on Large Gatherings. Pursuant to Chapter 14B-7 of the Dallas City Code, the city manager shall establish an order to limit the size of gatherings to no more than 500 people. Section 9. Effective Date. This Proclamation shall take effect immediately upon its issuance by the Mayor of the City of Dallas. I HEREBY DECLARE A LOCAL STATE OF DISASTER WITHIN THE CITY OF DALLAS to continue until March 19, 2020 subject to the continuation or renewal of the City Council of the City of Dallas upon the expiration of seven (7) days as provided by Texas Government Code Section 418.108. ACCORDINGLY, I further proclaim activation of the City Emergency Management Plan and the activation of all other charter, statutory, and ordinance powers vested in me and all officers of the City of Dallas to act in the premises and for the purposes stated. Prompt and general publicity is hereby proclaimed and ordered as to the issuance of this Proclamation. 3 ORDERED this 12th day of March, 2020, in the City of Dallas, Dallas County, Texas, in witness whereof I hereunto subscribe my name. Mayor Eric Johnson City of Dallas Filed with me, City Secretary Bilierae Johnson of the City of Dallas this 12" day of March, 2020, by Mayor Eric Johnson whose signature I hereby certify is true and genuine, with general publicity of the foregoing Proclamation being put into effect the same date as the signing thereof. Bilierae Johnson City Secretary City of Dallas 4</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
