<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix=" " id="us/or/cities/portland/mayor/declarations/2020-03-12">
  <num type="Declaration">Order of 2020-03-12</num>
  <heading>Emergency Declaration for the City of Portland, Oregon</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-12</effective>
    <expiration>2020-03-26</expiration>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-12.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-12</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>PORTLAND CITY NO93 d 1851 OFFICE OF MAYOR TED WHEELER CITY OF PORTLAND EMERGENCY DECLARATION FOR THE CITY OF PORTLAND, OREGON IN THE MATTER OF DECLARING A LOCAL EMERGENCY Declaration WITHIN THE CITY OF PORTLAND WHEREAS, the continued spread of the COVID-19 virus creates an extreme risk to public health, government and business continuity, and the local economy of the City of Portland, across the entire City; and WHEREAS, the following conditions now exist in the impacted area: the COVID-19 virus continues to spread, vulnerable populations are most at risk from the virus, personal protective equipment for first responders is depleted, workforce may become depleted resulting in reduced services, increased demand for sanitation resources for populations experiencing homelessness, shelters becoming overwhelmed; and WHEREAS, State statute, the Portland City Charter and Portland City Code serve as a basis for authorization to make an emergency declaration and take emergency control in the public's interest; and WHEREAS, I, Ted Wheeler, as Mayor of the City of Portland, declare the area described in the first paragraph above, to be in a State of Emergency. I further declare that the duration of the declaration of emergency shall be from: 08:00 on the 12th day of March 2020, to and including 08:00 on the 26th day of March 2020. The duration of the emergency declaration shall be limited to two weeks, but it may be extended in two-week increments. I further declare that for the duration of the emergency, unless otherwise specified by the Mayor, the current bureau assignments to the members of the City Council shall remain in effect as delegated authority under PCC 15.08.020.A. I further declare that, in addition to any other power that may lawfully be exercised by local government, the powers listed in PCC 15.08.020.B are vested in the Mayor. 1221 SW FOURTH AVENUE, SUITE 340 + PORTLAND, OREGON 97204 PHONE: (503) 823-4120 * FAX: (503) 823-3588 + MayorWheeler@PortlandOregon.gov Printed on 100% recycled paper I further declare that to protect the health of City employees, the Bureau of Human Resources may issue emergency rules or guidance on the use of sick leave, teleworking, or other policies that shall be in effect only for the duration of the emergency. I further declare that the Director of the Portland Bureau of Emergency Management shall take all necessary steps authorized by law to coordinate the response and recovery of this emergency, including but not limited to, requesting assistance from the State of Oregon and Multnomah County. Dated THIS 12th day of March, 2020 City of Portland, Oregon By: APPROVED AS TO FORM: Tracy Reeve, City Attorney For Portland, Oregon 1221 SW FOURTH AVENUE, SUITE 340 + PORTLAND, OREGON 97204 PHONE: (503) 823-4120 * FAX: (503) 823-3588 + MayorWheeler@PortlandOregon.gov Printed on 100% recycled paper</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
