<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="" id="us/ca/cities/san-francisco/mayor/proclamations/2020-02-25">
  <num type="Proclamation"/>
  <heading>Proclamation by the Mayor Declaring the Existence of a Local Emergency</heading>
  <heading type="oll">San Francisco, CA Proclamation by the Mayor Declaring the Existence of a Local Emergency, February 25, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-02-25</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-02-25.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-02-25</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>OFFICE OF THE MAYOR HAND COUNTY OF THE CITY LONDON N. BREED SAN FRANCISCO ONVH1 NVS10 MAYORVED BOARD OF SUPERVISORS SAN FRANCISCO 2020 FEB 27 PM 2:42 PROCLAMATION BY THE MAYOR DECLARING AK THE EXISTENCE OF A LOCAL EMERGENCY WHEREAS, California Government Code Sections 8550 et seq., San Francisco Charter Section 3.100(13) and Chapter 7 of the San Francisco Administrative Code empower the Mayor to proclaim the existence of a local emergency, subject to concurrence by the Board of Supervisors as provided in the Charter, in the case of an emergency threatening the lives, property or welfare of the City and County or its citizens; and WHEREAS, The United States has confirmed cases of individuals who have a severe acute respiratory illness caused by a novel (new) coronavirus ("COVID-19" or "the virus") first detected in Wuhan, Hubei Province, People's Republic of China ("China"). The virus was first reported in China on December 31, 2019. As of February 24, 2020, the World Health Organization ("WHO") has reported approximately 77,262 confirmed cases of COVID-19 in China, more than the number of confirmed cases of Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS) during its 2003 outbreak. An additional 2,069 cases have been confirmed across 29 other countries; in many of these cases, the infected individuals had not visited China. More than 2,500 people have died from the virus, including 23 outside of China. The number of confirmed cases has continued to escalate dramatically over a short period of time; and WHEREAS, WHO officials now report that sustained human-to-human transmission of the virus is occurring. Transmission from an asymptomatic individual has been documented. Although the majority of individuals infected with COVID-19 recover from the disease without special treatment, approximately 1 in 6 may become seriously ill. Manifestations of severe disease have included severe pneumonia, acute respiratory distress syndrome, septic shock, and multi-organ failure. Approximately 2% of the people confirmed infected with COVID-19 have died; and WHEREAS, On January 30, 2020, WHO declared the COVID-19 outbreak a public health emergency of international concern, and on January 31, 2020, the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services declared a Public Health Emergency for the United States; and WHEREAS, The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention ("CDC") has determined that the virus presents a serious public health threat, requiring coordination among state OFFICE OF THE MAYOR I OF THE CITY AN AND COUNTYO IONVUI NYS 10 LONDON N. BREED SAN FRANCISCO MAYOR and local health departments to ensure readiness for potential health threats associated with the virus; and WHEREAS, The CDC has issued guidance to local and State health departments, including San Francisco's Department of Public Health ("DPH"), concerning risk assessment and public health management of persons with potential exposure to COVID- 19. These guidelines require DPH to make extraordinary efforts to monitor ongoing communicable disease threats and prepare for management of individuals who may have been exposed to COVID-19; and WHEREAS, DPH, the Department of Emergency Management, and other City partners have been working successfully and diligently to implement CDC guidelines, but now require additional tools and resources to protect the public health given the current state of the epidemic and the need for a sustained response; and WHEREAS, The City's Director of Public Health has determined that DPH cannot comply with the CDC's guidance without immediate action beyond the City's ordinary response capabilities, including directing personnel and resources from other City departments to assist with the ongoing and developing threat of COVID-19; and WHEREAS, Conditions of extreme peril to the safety of persons and property have arisen; and WHEREAS, The Mayor does hereby proclaim that the aforesaid conditions of extreme peril warrant and necessitate the proclamation of the existence of a local emergency, NOW, THEREFORE, I, London N. Breed, Mayor of the City and County of San Francisco, proclaim the existence, effective immediately on February 25, 2020, of an emergency within the City and County threatening the lives, property or welfare of the City and County and its citizens; It is further ordered that: (1) All City and County officers and employees take all steps requested by the Director of Public Health to prevent the spread of COVID-19 and to prevent or alleviate illness or death due to the virus; and 2 OFFICE OF THE MAYOR F THE CITY HAND COUNTY ON LONDON N. BREED SAN FRANCISCO MAYOR (2) All City and County officers and employees take all steps requested by the Director of Public Health to qualify the City for reimbursement from the Federal Emergency Management Agency and for other state and federal relief as may be available to reimburse the City for the expenses it incurs in addressing this emergency; and I further proclaim and order that: By the terms of this emergency declaration the government of the City and County of San Francisco is organized under the provisions of the Incident Command System (ICS), which system forms an essential part of the City's Emergency Operations Plan. The head of each City department and agency shall observe his or her proper relationship in the command structure outlined by the system and shall respond to the orders and requests of the Lead Department designated to exercise supervision over his or her department during the course of this emergency; Because of the extreme peril to its residents and visitors, the Governor of the State of California is hereby requested to include the area of the City and County of San Francisco in any emergency declaration by the State, and is further requested to ensure that the City and County is included in any emergency declaration that may be issued by the President of the United States. And I further proclaim and order that: This declaration of a local emergency shall continue to exist until it is terminated by the Mayor or the Board of Supervisors. All departments of the City and County of San Francisco are strictly ordered to cooperate with the requests for material and personnel resources that may emanate from the Incident Command Staff of the City and County which is located in the Emergency Command Center of the City and County of San Francisco. DATED: 2/25/2020 but breed Mayor of San Francisco n:\govern\as2020\9690082\01430676.doc w</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
