<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Tulsa Executive Order" id="us/ok/cities/tulsa/mayor/orders/2020-03-17">
  <num type="Order">2020-02</num>
  <heading>Order and Proclamation Issued Pursuant to Civil Emergency Authority Limiting and Closing Certain Commercial Businesses</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-17.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://www.cityoftulsa.org/media/12519/2020-02.pdf"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-17</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>OFFICE OF THE MAYOR CITY OF TULSA, OKLAHOMA EXECUTIVE ORDER NO. 2020- 2 ORDER AND PROCLAMATION ISSUED PURSUANT TO CIVIL EMERGENCY AUTHORITY LIMITING AND CLOSING CERTAIN COMMERCIAL BUSINESSES WHEREAS, on March 16, 2020, pursuant to Tulsa Revised Ordinances, Title 8, Section 100, et seq. and my authority as Mayor, in Executive Order 2020-01, I proclaimed a civil emergency in the City of Tulsa; and WHEREAS, on March 1 1, 2020 the World Health Organization (WHO) declared the coronavirus COVID-19 disease to be a pandemic; and WHEREAS, on March 13, 2020 the President of the United States declared a National Emergency; due to the COVID-19 Virus pandemic and WHEREAS, on March 15, 2020, the Governor of the State of Oklahoma has declared an emergency caused by the impending threat of COVID-19 to the people of this State and the public's peace, health and safety; and WHEREAS, it is my continuing duty as Mayor to protect the health and safety of the City and its inhabitants, to preserve the peace, and to provide civil defense and emergency functions; and WHEREAS, Tulsa Revised Ordinances Title 8, Section 202 (G) provides that the Mayor, after proclaiming a civil emergency may in the interest of public safety and welfare make "Such other orders as are imminently necessary for the protection of life and property." Therefore, by the power vested in me as Mayor of the City of Tulsa, I find that due to the potential for rapid community spread and transmission of the COVID-19 virus, immediate attention is required to protect public health, safety and welfare, it is hereby declared and ORDERED, as follows: 1. Restaurants, food courts, cafes, coffeehouses, and other places of public accommodation offering food and beverage are closed for dine-in customers and guests and for on- premises consumption, are restricted and limited to curbside, drive-thru, takeout and delivery services, excluding institutional or in-house food cafeterias that serve residents, employees, and clients of businesses, child care facilities, hospitals, and long-term care facilities. 2. The following commercial establishments and places of public accommodation shall be and are hereby closed to ingress, egress, use, and occupancy by members of the public: a. Bars, taverns, brew pubs, breweries, microbreweries, distilleries, wineries, tasting rooms, clubs, and other places of public accommodation offering alcoholic beverages for on-premises consumption. b. Hookah bars, cigar bars, and vaping lounges offering their products for on premises consumption. C. Theaters, cinemas, indoor and outdoor performance venues, and museums. d. Gymnasiums, fitness centers, recreation centers, indoor sports facilities, indoor exercise facilities, exercise studios, and spas. e. Amusement parks, arcades, bingo halls, bowling alleys, indoor climbing facilities, skating rinks, trampoline parks, and other similar recreational or entertainment facilities. 3. This Executive Order does not prohibit an employee, contractor, vendor, or supplier of a place of public accommodation from entering, exiting, using, or occupying that place of public accommodation in their professional capacity. 4. The restrictions imposed by this Executive Order do not apply to any of the following: a. Places of public accommodation that offer food and beverage not for on-premises consumption, including grocery stores, markets, convenience stores, pharmacies, drug stores, and food pantries, other than those portions of the place of public accommodation subject to the requirements of section; b. Health care facilities, child care facilities, residential care facilities, congregate care facilities, and juvenile justice facilities; C. Crisis shelters, soup kitchens, or similar institutions; and d. Restaurants and food courts inside the secured zones of airports. 5. For purposes of this Executive Order, "place of public accommodation" means a business, or an educational, refreshment, entertainment, or recreation facility, or an institution of any kind, whether licensed or not, whose goods, services, facilities, privileges, advantages, or accommodations are extended, offered, sold, or otherwise made available to the public. 6. This Executive Order does not alter any of the obligations under law of an employer affected by this Executive Order to its employees or to the employees of another employer. The closings of bars, etc., set forth in Section 2 (a) of this Executive Order shall take effect immediately, and the remainder of the limitations, restrictions, and closings herein shall be effective this 17th day of March, 2020, at 11:59 P. m., and all shall continue in effect indefinitely. G. T. Bynum, Mayor MAR 1 7 2020 ATTEST: APPROVED: City Clerk City Attorney</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
