<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Tulsa Executive Order" id="us/ok/cities/tulsa/mayor/orders/2020-03-16">
  <num type="Order">2020-01</num>
  <heading>Order Proclaiming Existence of a Civil Emergency</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-16</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-16.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://www.cityoftulsa.org/media/12505/executive-order-2020-01.pdf"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-16</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>OFFICE OF THE MAYOR CITY OF TULSA, OKLAHOMA EXECUTIVE ORDER NO. 2020-_ ORDER PROCLAIMING EXISTENCE OF A CIVIL EMERGENCY WHEREAS, on March 11, 2020 the World Health Organization (WHO) declared the coronavirus COVID-19 disease to be a pandemic; and WHEREAS, on March 13, 2020 the President of the United States declared a National Emergency; due to the COVID-19 Virus pandemic and WHEREAS, on March 15, 2020, the Governor of the State of Oklahoma has declared an emergency caused by the impending threat of COVID-19 to the people of this State and the public's peace, health and safety; and WHEREAS, the Centers for Disease Control (CDC) has advised certain American cities and counties to limit public gatherings of 50 people; and WHEREAS, it is my duty as Mayor to protect the health and safety of the City and its inhabitants, to preserve the peace, and to provide civil defense and emergency functions; and WHEREAS, Title 37 Tulsa Revised Ordinances (TRO) Chapter 14 regulates the issuance of special event permits; Section 1409 of that Chapter allows revocation of a special event permit for a perceived threat to public health, safety or welfare; Therefore, by the power vested in me as Mayor of the City or Tulsa, I hereby proclaim the existence of a civil emergency in the City of Tulsa and further, it is hereby declared and ORDERED, as follows: 1. All events or gatherings of fifty (50) people or more, in or on a City-owned or City-operated facility or property, are hereby banned, until at least April 15, 2020, when the pandemic emergency will be reassessed; and 2. All special event permits, issued under the authority of Title 37 TRO Sections 1400 through 1415, with projected attendance of fifty (50) people or more, are hereby revoked, and as of this date, no further such special event permits shall be issued and no such special events may be held in the City of Tulsa until at least April 15, 2020, when the pandemic emergency will be reassessed. This Executive Order shall take effect this day of March, 2020. G. T. Bynum, Mayor City Attorney ATTEST: Deputy City Clerk</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
