<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of Fresno Emergency Order" id="us/ca/cities/fresno/city-manager/orders/2020-03-17">
  <num type="Order">2020-01</num>
  <heading>Emergency Order 2020-01 Restaurants and Bars</heading>
  <heading type="oll">Restaurants and Bars, March 17, 2020</heading>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-17</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-03-17.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-17</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>Y OF FRESNO INCOR PRORATED OCT . MY 12, 18 85 . WILMA QUAN City Manager FROM THE OFFICE OF THE CITY MANAGER: EMERGENCY ORDER 2020-01 RESTAURANTS AND BARS As the Director of Emergency Services pursuant to Fresno Municipal Code Section 2-505, and by the powers invested in me by Fresno Municipal Code Section 2-506, I hereby issue the following orders, to be effective immediately and for so long as the City's declared emergency is in effect related to COVID-19: 1) Definitions: a) Restaurant: Any establishment that sells food for consumption on-premises. b) Food Court: Any establishment that sells food for consumption on-premises in a shared setting with other establishments. c) Bar and tavern: Any establishment with the following types of California Alcoholic Beverage Control licenses: i) 40 - On Sale Beer (Bar, Tavern) i) 42 - On Sale Beer &amp; Wine - Public Premises (Bar, Tavern) iv) 51 - Club ii) 48 - On Sale General - Public Premises (Bar, Night Club) v) 57 - Special On Sale General vi) 60 - On Sale Beer - Seasonal vii) 61 - On Sale Beer - Public Premises 2) Restaurants, Food Courts, and other establishments that offer on-premises dining are prohibited from allowing consumption of food on-premises. Delivery, drive-thru, and pick-up options are allowed. 3) Bars and taverns shall be closed. 4) No City permits for special events shall be granted. 5) No temporary ABC license shall be authorized by the City. The Fresno Police Department and City Attorney's Office Code Enforcement Division shall enforce this Order. 7) The Order shall be subject to amendment or repeal at any time, and shall not be deemed to confer any contractual obligations, property rights, or assume any City liability. City of Fresno City Hall . 2600 Fresno Street . Fresno, California 93721-3600 (559) 621-7768 . FAX (559) 621-7776 . www.fresno.gov Emergency Order 2020-01 Restaurants and Bars March 17, 2020 Page 2 of 2 8) If any provision of this Order or its application to any person or circumstance is held to be invalid, then the reminder of the Order, including the application of such part or provision to other persons or circumstances, shall not be affected and shall continue in full force and effect. To this end, the provisions of this Order are severable. 9) This Order shall be immediately translated into Spanish and Hmong, and accommodations made for all disabled persons to read its contents; it shall also be distributed to all local media and made prominently available on the City's website. 10) Pursuant to Fresno Municipal Code section 2-512, violations of this Order shall be punishable as a misdemeanor upon conviction by a fine of not exceeding one thousand dollars or by imprisonment for a term of not exceeding one year, or by both such fine and imprisonment. IT IS SO ORDERED. Director of Emergency Services March 17, 2020 2:00pm Wilma Quan Date Time City Manager</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
