<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="City of San Diego, CA Executive Order NO." id="us/ca/cities/san-diego/mayor/orders/2020-1">
  <num type="Executive Order">2020-1</num>
  <heading/>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Issued</status>
    <effective>2020-03-16</effective>
    <expiration>2020-03-31</expiration>
    <link type="pdf" url="./2020-1.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-16</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>SAN DIEGO . STATE OF THE C City of San Diego EXECUTIVE ORDER NO. 2020-1 By the Mayor On March 12, 2020, I issued a proclamation of local emergency in preparation and response to the spread of the COVID-19 virus in our community. On March 13, 2020, I ordered measures to be taken across the City to protect members of the public and City employees from an undue risk of contracting the COVID-19 virus including closure of libraries and recreation centers. It is imperative that the City of San Diego, under my authority as the Mayor, implement locally all guidance and directives currently available from federal, state, and local public health officials to stem the spread of the virus and protect public safety and welfare. The measures outlined in this order pertain to matters reasonably related to the protection of life and property. On January 31, 2020, United States Health and Human Services Secretary Alex M. Azar II declared a public health emergency for the United States to aid the nation's healthcare community in responding to COVID-19. On February 19, 2020, the County of San Diego Board of Supervisors ratified the Declaration of Local Health Emergency. On March 11, 2020, the World Health Organization declared the COVID-19 outbreak. On March 13, 2020, President Donald J. Trump issued a Proclamation on Declaring a National Emergency Concerning the Novel Coronavirus Disease, COVID-19, Outbreak. The City of San Diego is bolstering efforts to promote sanitation and social distancing measures. We must do everything we can to slow the pace of community spread and avoid unnecessary strain on our medical system. To aid in our efforts, under the emergency authorities vested in my office under the laws of the City of San Diego, today I am ordering that a series of temporary restrictions be placed on certain establishments throughout our City in which large numbers of people gather and remain in close proximity. By virtue of authority vested in me as Mayor of the City of San Diego pursuant to the provisions of the City Charter, San Diego Municipal Code section 51.0105, and California Government Code section 8634 to promulgate, issue, and enforce rules, regulations, and orders, I hereby declare the following orders to be necessary for the protection of life and property and I hereby order, effective at 11:59 p.m. tonight, until March 31, 2020 at 12:00 p.m., that: 1. All public or private gatherings, to be defined as any event or convening that brings together 50 or more people in a single room or single space at the same time, such as an auditorium, stadium, arena, theater, church, casino, large conference room, meeting hall, cafeteria, or any other indoor or outdoor space, are prohibited. All non-essential social gatherings of any size are strongly discouraged. THE CITY OF SAN IN DIEGO . STATE O City of San Diego EXECUTIVE ORDER NO. 2020-1 By the Mayor 2. All bars, adult entertainment establishments, and nightclubs in the City of San Diego shall be closed to the public and all restaurants and business establishments that serve food in the City of San Diego shall be prohibited from serving food and beverage for consumption on premises. Restaurants and business establishments that serve food may continue to operate for purposes of preparing and offering food to customers via delivery service, to be picked up, or by drive-thru. For those establishments offering food pick-up options, proprietors are directed to establish social distancing practices for those patrons in the queue for pick-up. Facilities expressly exempted from this order include cafeterias, commissaries, and restaurants located within hospitals, skilled nursing facilities, and other healthcare facilities; grocery stores; pharmacies; and food banks. 3. Trucks and other vehicles engaged in the delivery of grocery items to grocery stores, when such items are to be made available for sale to the public, are hereby exempt from having to comply with any City rules and regulations that limit the hours for such deliveries. 4. All City of San Diego public buildings are to be closed to the general public. 5. City Departments will execute their Continuity of Operations Plans to maintain appropriate levels of essential services. The City will continue to provide these services including Police, Fire, Water, Wastewater and Trash Disposal. 6. The City of San Diego will enact a moratorium on utility shutoffs for utilities provided by the City of San Diego Public Utility Department and the City may develop a program for payment deferrals. 7. The City of San Diego will limit parking enforcement and issuance of citations to holiday or Sunday enforcement regulations, including no longer enforcing parking meters, yellow commercial zones, short-term green zones and 1- to 2-hour time parking zones. Red, white, blue, and other all-time enforcement areas will continue to be enforced to maintain public safety. Any violation of the above prohibitions may be referred for prosecution to the fullest extent of the law. Each individual officer should use their discretion in enforcing this order and always keep the intent of the order in mind. THE CITY OF SAN SAN DIEGO . STATE OF NOT SENTER VIGILANCE City of San Diego EXECUTIVE ORDER NO. 2020-1 By the Mayor In addition, I hereby issue a strong recommendation, consistent with Centers of Disease Control guidance from March 16, 2020 to avoid non-essential gatherings to the extent possible, to the leaders of the City's houses of worship and urge them, in the strongest possible terms, to limit gatherings on their premises and to explore and implement ways to practice their respective faiths while observing social distancing practices. This order may be extended before it expires on March 31, 2020. / Dated: March 16, 2020 Mayor Kevin L. Faulconer</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
