<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="MOTION NO." id="us/ca/cities/san-francisco/board-of-supervisors/motions/M20-38">
  <num type="Motion">M20-38</num>
  <heading>Motion Ratifying the March 6, 2020, City and County of San Francisco Health Officer’s Declaration of Local Health Emergency, Regarding Novel Coronavirus Disease 2019 (covid-19).</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-03-06</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./M20-38.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://sfgov.legistar.com/LegislationDetail.aspx?From=Alert&amp;ID=4391902&amp;GUID=8B2C6DE1-B28C-46DB-99DF-B2ABA97E9BA2&amp;Options=ID|Text|&amp;Search=coronavirus"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-10</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>FILE NO. 200265 MOTION NO. M20-38 Ratifying the County Health Officer's Declaration of a Local Health Emergency Regarding N Novel Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19)] 3 Motion ratifying the March 6, 2020, City and County of San Francisco Health Officer's 4 Declaration of Local Health Emergency, regarding Novel Coronavirus Disease 2019 5 (COVID-19). 6 7 WHEREAS, California Health and Safety Code Section 101080 authorizes the local 8 health officer to declare a local health emergency in the health officer's jurisdiction whenever 9 the health officer reasonably determines that there is an imminent and proximate threat to the 10 public health due to the introduction of any contagious, infectious, or communicable disease; 11 and 12 WHEREAS, On February 25, 2020, San Francisco Mayor London N. Breed issued a 13 Proclamation Declaring the Existence of a Local Emergency under Government Code 14 Sections 8550 et seq., San Francisco Charter Section 3.100(14), and San Francisco 15 Administrative Code Chapter 7 ("Mayor's Local Emergency Declaration"), establishing the 16 existence of an emergency within the City and County of San Francisco due to the ongoing 17 spread of a novel coronavirus, referred to as Coronavirus Disease 2019 or "COVID-19"; and 18 WHEREAS, On March 3, 2020, the Board of Supervisors concurred by motion with the 19 Mayor's Local Emergency Declaration, and in the actions taken by the Mayor to meet the 20 emergency; and 21 WHEREAS, On March 5, 2020, the Mayor's Office and the San Francisco Department 22 of Public Health announced that two individuals in San Francisco had contracted COVID-19 23 without any known avenue of transmission, suggesting the contagion was community- 24 acquired by the individuals and that the virus is circulating in the Bay Area; and 25 Supervisors Yee; Peskin BOARD OF SUPERVISORS Page WHEREAS, On March 6, 2020, the City and County of San Francisco Health Officer N ("Health Officer") declared a Local Health Emergency based on the scientific literature, facts 3 and circumstances described in documents on file with the Clerk of the Board of Supervisors 4 in File No. 200265, finding an imminent and proximate threat to public health from the 5 introduction of COVID-19 in the City and County of San Francisco; and 6 WHEREAS, By declaring a local health emergency, the Health Officer activates the 7 provisions of California Health and Safety Code Section 101085, California Government Code 8 Section 8659, and as otherwise provided for by law; and 9 WHEREAS, Under California Health and Safety Code Section 101080, a Health 10 Officer's declaration of a local health emergency may remain in effect for up to seven days, 11 and must be ratified by the Board of Supervisors in order to continue beyond that period; and 12 WHEREAS, the Health Officer, based on the current facts regarding the continuing 13 spread of COVID-19, thinks the emergency relating to COVID-19 will persist beyond seven 14 days; and; 15 WHEREAS, The Health Officer respectfully requests that the San Francisco Board of 16 Supervisors ratify the Health Officer's Declaration of Local Health Emergency dated March 6, 17 2020, on file with the Clerk of the Board of Supervisors in File No. 200265; now, therefore, be 18 it 19 MOVED, That San Francisco Board of Supervisors hereby ratifies the Health Officer's 20 Declaration of Local Health Emergency dated March 6, 2020, and that the Local Health 21 Emergency shall continue beyond March 13, 2020, until, in consultation with the Health 22 Officer, the Board of Supervisors proclaims the Local Health Emergency is terminated. 23 n:\health\as2020\2000350\01434192.docx 24 25 Supervisors Yee; Peskin BOARD OF SUPERVISORS Page 2 City and County of San Francisco City Hall 1 Dr. Carlton B. Goodlett Place Tails San Francisco, CA 94102-4689 Motion: M20-038 File Number: 200265 Date Passed: March 10, 2020 Motion ratifying the March 6, 2020, City and County of San Francisco Health Officer's Declaration of Local Health Emergency, regarding Novel Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19). March 10, 2020 Board of Supervisors - APPROVED Walton and Yee Ayes: 10 - Fewer, Mandelman, Mar, Peskin, Preston, Ronen, Safai, Stefani, Absent: 1 - Haney File No. 200265 I hereby certify that the foregoing Motion was APPROVED.on 3/10/2020 by the Board of Supervisors of the City and County of San Francisco. Angela Calvillo Clerk of the Board City and County of San Francisco Page 1 Printed at 10:08 am on 3/11/20</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
