<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="MOTION NO." id="us/ca/cities/san-francisco/board-of-supervisors/motions/M20-28">
  <num type="Motion">M20-28</num>
  <heading>Motion Concurring in the February 25, 2020, Proclamation by Mayor London N. Breed Declaring the Existence of a Local Emergency in Connection with Preparations the City and County of San Francisco Is Making in Response to the Serious and Imminent Threat of an Outbreak of the Novel Coronavirus COVID-19 ("Covid-19") and Compliance with the Center for Disease Control's Guidance Regarding Responding to Covid-19, and Concurring in the Actions Taken to Meet the Emergency.</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-02-25</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./M20-28.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url=""/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-03</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>FILE NO. 200228 MOTION NO. M20-28 [Concurring in Proclamation of Local Emergency - Coronavirus Response] 2 3 Motion concurring in the February 25, 2020, proclamation by Mayor London N. Breed A declaring the existence of a local emergency in connection with preparations the City 5 and County of San Francisco is making in response to the serious and imminent threat 6 of an outbreak of the novel coronavirus COVID-19 ("COVID-19") and compliance with 7 the Center for Disease Control's guidance regarding responding to COVID-19, and 8 concurring in the actions taken to meet the emergency. 9 10 WHEREAS, On February 25, 2020, Mayor London N. Breed declared a local 11 emergency to exist in connection with preparations the City is making to address the spread 12 of the novel coronavirus COVID-19 ("COVID-19"); and 13 WHEREAS, The Mayor has transmitted a copy of that Proclamation Declaring the 14 Existence of a Local Emergency to the Board of Supervisors, and such copy is on file with the 15 Clerk of the Board of Supervisors in File No. 200228; and 16 WHEREAS, Government Code Sections 8550 et seq. and Charter Section 3.100 17 provide for the concurrence by members of the Board of Supervisors in such emergency 18 declaration and in action taken by the Mayor to meet the emergency; and 19 WHEREAS, Public health officials have detected COVID-19 in 33 countries around the 20 world, and the number of cases continues to increase; the Center for Disease Control ("CDC") 21 has determined that COVID-19 presents a serious and imminent threat, requiring coordination 22 among state and local health departments to ensure readiness for potential health impacts 23 associated with the virus; and 24 WHEREAS, CDC has issued guidance to local health departments including the San 25 Francisco Department of Public Health concerning risk assessment, monitoring Supervisors Yee; Mandelman BOARD OF SUPERVISORS Page communicable disease threats, and public health management of people exposed to COVID- N 19; and WHEREAS, The Director of Public Health has determined that DPH cannot comply 4 with CDC's guidance and respond to the serious and imminent threat to public health without 5 immediate action beyond the City's ordinary capabilities, including directing personnel and 6 resources from other City departments to assist with the ongoing and developing threat of 7 COVID-19; the Mayor has directed City officers and employees to take steps required by the 8 Director Public Health to prevent the spread of COVID-19 and to prevent or alleviate illness or 9 death due to the virus; and 10 WHEREAS, The Mayor has found the aforesaid conditions of extreme peril justify and 11 require a proclamation of the existence of a local emergency; and 12 WHEREAS, The Mayor has directed the head of each department and agency to 13 observe his or her proper relationship in the command structure of the Incident Command 14 System, and be responsive to the orders and requests of the Lead Department designated to 15 exercise supervision over his or her department during the course of this emergency; and 16 WHEREAS, This declaration of a local emergency shall be deemed to continue until it 17 is terminated by the Mayor or the Board of Supervisors; all departments of the City and 18 County of San Francisco are strictly enjoined to cooperate with the requests for material and 19 personnel resources by the City's Incident Command System staff located in the Emergency 20 Operations Center; now, therefore, be it 21 MOVED, That the Board of Supervisors concurs with the Proclamation by the Mayor 22 Declaring the Existence of Local Emergency issued on February 25, 2020, and in the actions 23 taken by the Mayor to meet the emergency. 24 25 n:\govern\as202019690082\01431082.docx Supervisors Yee; Mandelman BOARD OF SUPERVISORS Page 2 AND COUNTY DID City and County of San Francisco City Hall 1 Dr. Carlton B. Goodlett Place Tails San Francisco, CA 94102-4689 NOTVIS - OOBIN Motion: M20-028 File Number: 200228 Date Passed: March 03, 2020 Motion concurring in the February 25, 2020, proclamation by Mayor London N. Breed declaring the existence of a local emergency in connection with preparations the City and County of San Francisco is making in response to the serious and imminent threat of an outbreak of the novel coronavirus COVID-19 ("COVID-19") and compliance with the Center for Disease Control's guidance regarding responding to COVID-19, and concurring in the actions taken to meet the emergency. March 03, 2020 Board of Supervisors - APPROVED Ayes: 11 - Fewer, Haney, Mandelman, Mar, Peskin, Preston, Ronen, Safai, Stefani, Walton and Yee File No. 200228 I hereby certify that the foregoing Motion was APPROVED on 3/3/2020 by the Board of Supervisors of the City and County of San Francisco. Angela Calvillo Clerk of the Board City and County of San Francisco Page I Printed at 1:19 pm on 3/4/20</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
